<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="admin-man-sect-boot-process">
  <title>Boot Process</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Boot Process</primary></indexterm>
  
  <para>
    This section describes the boot process of Qlustar cluster-nodes.
  </para>
  
  <section id="admin-man-sect-comp-node-boot">
    <title>Compute-node booting</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Boot Process</primary>
    <secondary>Compute-node booting</secondary></indexterm>

    <para> 
      The boot process of the compute-nodes follows precise rules. It takes place in four
      steps:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The PXE boot ROM of the network card sends a DHCP request. If the node is already
	  registered in QluMan, the request is answered by the DHCP server running on the
	  head-node(s), allowing the adapter to configure its basic IP settings.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The boot ROM requests a PXE loader program from the TFTP server on the head-node (the
	  TFTP server specified by DHCP could also be on another node, but this is not the
	  default). The PXE loader is then sent to the compute-node via TFTP.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  PXELinux downloads the Qlustar Linux kernel and the assigned RAM-disk (OS) image,
	  boots the kernel and mounts the RAM-disk.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The usual Linux boot process proceeds.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
  </section>

  <section id="admin-man-sect-tftp-boot-serv">
    <title>TFTP Boot Server</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Boot Process</primary>
    <secondary>TFTP Boot Server</secondary></indexterm>
      
    <para>
      The Advanced TFTP server transfers the boot image to the compute-nodes. All files that
      should be served by tftp must reside in the directory
      <filename>/var/lib/tftpboot</filename>. On a Qlustar installation, it contains three
      symbolic links:
    </para>
    
<screen>
pxelinux.0 -> <filename>/usr/lib/syslinux/pxelinux.0</filename>
pxelinux.cfg -> <filename>/etc/qlustar/pxelinux.cfg</filename>
qlustar -> <filename>/var/lib/qlustar</filename>
</screen>

    <para>
      The directory <filename>/etc/qlustar/pxelinux.cfg</filename> contains the PXE boot
      configuration files for the compute-nodes. There is a default configuration that applies
      to any node without an assigned custom boot configuration in QluMan. For every host with
      a custom boot configuration, QluMan adds a symbolic link pointing to the actual
      configuration file. The links are named after the node's <parameter>Hostid</parameter>,
      which you can find out with the <command>gethostip</command> command. For more details
      about how to define boot configurations see the corresponding section of the
      &QLUMANGUIDE;.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="admin-man-sect-RAM-disk-img">
    <title>RAM-disk image</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Boot Process</primary>
    <secondary>RAM-disk image</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
      The RAM-disk image is the file-system holding the node OS that is mounted as the root
      filesystem of the compute-nodes. It is assembled on the head-node(s) from the image
      modules, you are able to select in QluMan. Every RAM-disk image contains at least the
      core module. See the corresponding section of the &QLUMANGUIDE; for more details. All
      available image modules are displayed and selectable in QluMan and the configuration and
      assembly of images is done automatically from within QluMan.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
	By default, the root password of a Qlustar OS image and hence the node booting it, is
	taken from the head-node(s) <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file and is therefore the
	same as on the head-node(s). If you want to change this, you can call
	<command>qlustar-image-reconfigure &lt;image-name&gt;</command>. (Replacing
	&lt;image-name&gt; with the actual name of the image). You can then specify a different
	root password for the node OS image.
      </para>
    </note>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  Changelogs
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Any Qlustar node OS image contains changelogs of the various image modules it is
	    composed of. They are located in the directory
	    <filename>/usr/share/doc/qlustar-image</filename>. The main changelog file is
	    <filename>core.changelog.gz</filename>. The other files are automatically
	    generated. The files <filename>*.packages.version.gz</filename> lists the packages
	    each module is made of. The files <filename>*.contents.changelog*.gz</filename>
	    lists the files that were changed between each version, and
	    <filename>*.packages.changelog*.gz</filename> list differences in the package list
	    and versions. Hence, you always have detailed information about what has been
	    changed in new images as well as the package sources of their content.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </section>
    
  <section id="admin-man-sect-qluman-execd">
    <title>QluMan Remote Execution Server</title>
    <indexterm><primary>QluMan</primary>
    <secondary>Remote Execution Server</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The QluMan execution server (<firstterm>qluman-execd</firstterm>) runs on any head- and
      compute-node of a Qlustar cluster. It is one of Qlustar's main components, responsible
      for executing remote commands as well as writing configurations to disk.
    </para>

    <section id="admin-man-sect-execd-dynamic-boot-scripts">
      <title>Dynamic Boot Script Excecution</title>
      <indexterm><primary>Boot Process</primary>
      <secondary>Dynamic Execution</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>
	When a compute-node boots and qluman-execd starts, it automatically performs some
	initialization/configuration tasks depending on the nodes QluMan configuration
	options. The following is a list of tasks managed by qluman-execd:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    Infiniband IP configuration
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Configuration of the Infiniband IPoIB address, if a node is configured to use
	      Infiniband within QluMan.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    Infiniband OpenSM startup
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Startup of OpenSM in case the node is configured to do so.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    IPMI IP configuration and channel selection
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Reconfiguration of the node's IPMI address, if a node is configured
	      correspondingly within QluMan.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
	For details about the configuration of the above components, see the corresponding
	section of the &QLUMANGUIDE;.
      </para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  If required for debugging, etc., the boot scripts managed by QluMan Execd can still
	  be executed manually, like normal System V boot scripts.
	</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
