<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="admin-man-sect-os-pkg-man">
  <title>OS Package Management</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Package Management</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    Ubuntu/Debian package management is based on the concept of package sources or 
    repositories. A configuration file <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> 
    (or separate files in the directory <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list.d</filename>)
    specifies the location of package sources.
  </para>
  <para>
    When a package is to be installed, all package source locations are checked whether they
    contain the desired package. If the desired package is found in only one package repository
    that one is taken, if it is found in more than one, then the package with the newest
    version is installed.
  </para>
  <section id="admin-man-sect-pkg-srcs">
    <title>Package sources</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Package Management</primary>
    <secondary>Package sources</secondary></indexterm>
    <para> 
      Package sources are usually specified in <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> and
      can be of many different types, like http, ftp, file, cdrom, &hellipsis; (see
      <command>man sources.list</command>). In a default Qlustar installation this file is
      empty, since all the Qlustar package sources are defined in the file
      <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list.d/qlustar.list</filename>. If your system has access to
      the Internet either directly or through a http proxy the file will look like this:
    </para>
    <screen>
deb http://repo.qlustar.com/repo/ubuntu 8.1-precise main universe non-free
deb http://repo.qlustar.com/repo/ubuntu 8.1-precise-proposed-updates main universe non-free
    </screen>
    <para>
      This enables access to the Qlustar 8.1 software repository.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	The file <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list.d/qlustar.list</filename> is managed by
	Qlustar and should usually not be edited manually. If you prefer not to receive the
	proposed updates, you can comment out the second line in the file. Be aware, that this
	will prevent you from receiving timely security updates as well.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section id="admin-man-sect-dpkg">
    <title>dpkg</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Package Management</primary>
    <secondary>dpkg</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <command>dpkg</command> (see <command>man dpkg</command>) is the
      basic package management tool for Ubuntu/Debian, comparable to
      rpm (<application>Red Hat Package Manager</application>). It is
      not capable of automatically resolving package dependencies.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="admin-man-sect-apt">
    <title>apt</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Package Management</primary><secondary>apt</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <command>apt</command> is the high-level package management tool for Ubuntu/Debian.
      <command>apt-get</command> (<command>man apt-get</command>)
      with its sub-commands provides all the functionality needed to maintain an Ubuntu/Debian
      system. A seem-less and fast upgrade of an Ubuntu/Debian system is typically performed
      running the two commands
    </para>
    <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
apt-get update</command>

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
apt-get dist-upgrade.</command>
    </screen>
    <para>
      Detailed upgrade instructions for a Qlustar system can be found
      in the <link
      xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qlustar-update-procedure">>Qlustar
      Update Guide</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      New packages can be installed by running 
      <command>apt-get install <replaceable>&lt;package name&gt;</replaceable></command>. If  
      <replaceable>package name</replaceable>
      depends on, or conflicts with other packages those will be automatically installed
      or removed upon confirmation.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="admin-man-sect-debian-pkg-altern">
    <title>Debian Package Alternatives</title>
     <indexterm><primary>Package Management</primary>
     <secondary>alternatives</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
       The possibility to concurrently run different versions of the same
       application on a single cluster is often crucial. In principle, this is achievable in
       a couple of ways, each one requiring more or less handwork depending on the type of
       application in question. Fortunately, Ubuntu/Debian provides the built-in "alternatives
       mechanism" to manage software versions in automated form. It has the additional
       advantage that it works appropriately for any kind of application.
     </para>
     <para>
       Let us consider the case of the GNU C compiler 
       <command>gcc</command> as an example of the situation described above. 
       Simply installing the <package>gcc</package> package via <command>apt-get
       </command> is all you need to do in this case. The alternatives are automatically
       configured for you.  
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
gcc --version</command>

gcc (Ubuntu/Linaro 4.6.3-1ubuntu5) 4.6.3
Copyright (C) 2011 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
     </screen>
     <para>
       This tells us that currently we are running the version 4.6.3 of the GNU C compiler. Let
       us inspect the <application>gcc</application> binary.
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
which gcc</command>

/usr/bin/gcc

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
ls -l /usr/bin/gcc</command>

lrwxrwxrwx ... /usr/bin/gcc -> /etc/alternatives/gcc
     </screen>
     <para>
       As we tried to locate the <command>gcc</command> command, we found that
       it was being executed from the <filename>/usr/bin</filename> path. However we 
       also discovered, that it’s a symbolic link pointing to 
       <filename>/etc/alternatives/gcc</filename>. The directory 
       <filename>/etc/alternatives</filename> is the place, where all the 
       software alternatives are configured in Ubuntu/Debian. Let us inspect a little further.
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
ls -l /etc/alternatives/gcc</command>

lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 16 Mai 13 19:23 /etc/alternatives/gcc -> /usr/bin/gcc-4.6

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
ls -l /usr/bin/gcc-4.6</command>

-rwxr-xr-x 1 root root 353216 Apr 16  2012 /usr/bin/gcc-4.6
     </screen>
     <para>
       We have another symbolic link, this time referring to 
       <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.6</filename> and a little digging afterward reveals that
       this is the real <command>gcc</command> executable. If alternative versions for a
       program are available, the alternatives system will create a link with the 
       name of the program in the default path pointing to the appropriate
       file in <filename>/etc/alternatives</filename>. This will finally link to the 
       executable, we actually want to use. Instead of manually manipulating these links,
       choosing a different default version for a program
       should be done using the command <command>update-alternatives</command>.
     </para>
     <para>
       Using <command>update-alternatives</command> we can quickly figure out which 
       alternatives are currently configured for a certain executable. Let us look at the 
       current setup of <application>gcc</application>.
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
update-alternatives --display gcc</command>

gcc - auto mode
link currently points to /usr/bin/gcc-4.6
/usr/bin/gcc-4.8 - priority 20
/usr/bin/gcc-4.6 - priority 50
Current ‘best’ version is /usr/bin/gcc-4.6
     </screen>
     <para>
       As you can see the current link points to <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.6</filename> as we
       already discovered. There is another alternative, namely
       <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.8</filename> with a priority of 20. The priority of
       <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.6</filename> is 50. The line <code>'gcc - auto mode’</code>
       means that the alternatives system will look for the package with the highest priority
       in order to use that executable.
     </para>
     <para>
       The last line in the above output says that the current best priority link is
       <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.6</filename>. Now if we want to use version 4.8 instead,
       we can tell <command>update-alternatives</command> to use exactly this version:
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
update-alternatives --config gcc</command>

There are 2 alternatives which provide ‘gcc’.
Selection Alternative
-----------------------------------------------
+ 1 /usr/bin/gcc-4.8
2 /usr/bin/gcc-4.6
*Press enter to keep the default[*], or type selection number:
     </screen>
     <para>
       We already knew by looking at the output that there where only two options. Now we
       can select which option we want. Let’s look at the output of the command again.
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
update-alternatives --display gcc</command>

gcc - status is manual.
link currently points to /usr/bin/4.8
/usr/bin/gcc-4.6 - priority 50
/usr/bin/gcc-4.8 - priority 20
Current ‘best’ version is /usr/bin/gcc-4.6.
     </screen>
     <para>
       We got a link currently pointing to <filename>/usr/bin/gcc-4.8</filename>
       so we quickly do the same checking as we did before.
     </para>
     <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
which gcc</command>

/usr/bin/gcc

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
ls -l /usr/bin/gcc</command>

lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 21 Sep  2 18:32 /usr/bin/gcc -> /etc/alternatives/gcc

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
ls -l /etc/alternatives/gcc</command>

lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 16 Sep  2 18:32 /etc/alternatives/gcc -> /usr/bin/gcc-4.8

<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
gcc --version</command>

gcc (Ubuntu 4.8.1-2ubuntu1~10.04.1) 4.8.1
Copyright (C) 2013 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
     </screen>
     <para>
       Only the link within <filename>/etc/alternatives</filename> has changed.
       When looking at the gcc version we see that it’s using the gcc-4.8 version.
     </para>
     <para>
       A further useful feature of <command>update-alternatives</command> is the
       possibility of creating groups of files having a relation with each other. These so
       called slaves will not only allow you to update the link to the desired executable but
       also any other information related to it like man pages, documentation, etc.
       Please consult <command>man update-alternatives</command> for more information on the
       capabilities of this powerful software versioning method.
     </para>
   </section>
 </section>
