<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "administration-manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-Updating-Qlustar">
  <title>Updating Qlustar</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Qlustar">
    <title>Qlustar updates</title>
    <para>
       Updating a <productname>Qlustar</productname> cluster is a multi-step process. The
       detailed steps depend on whether the update involves a kernel update or not (the release
       notes will mention it, if a new kernel is part of the update) and what module versions
       you have selected for your images. We'll explain the differences below. Follow the steps
       in the following order.
     </para>
     <section xml:id="updating-headnodes">
       <title>Updating the head-node(s)</title>
       <para>
	 Apply the standard <application>Debian</application> procedure to update the
	 head-node(s) installation. Execute as root:
       </para>
       <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
apt update</command>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
apt dist-upgrade</command>
       </screen>
       <para>
	 This will update all packages. In most cases, if new versions of the
	 <productname>Qlustar</productname> image module packages are available, this will also
	 automatically rebuild the images defined in <application>QluMan</application>. We
	 elaborate on this <xref linkend="image-update" xrefstyle="template: below"/>.
       </para>
       <para>
	 If the kernel was updated by this process reboot the head-node(s) after executing the
	 above commands, otherwise you're done with this step.
       </para>
     </section>
     <section xml:id="updating-chroots">
       <title>Updating the chroot(s)</title>
       <para>
	 This is either also a standard Debian or a standard CentOS upgrade as explained in the
	 <link
	 xlink:href="../First_Steps_Guide/index.html#sec-Adding-Software___blank___">First Step
	 Guide</link>. If you have setup multiple chroots, you'll have to update all of them.
       </para>
     </section>
     <section xml:id="updating-nodes">
       <title>Updating the nodes</title>
       <para>
	 If the update contains a new kernel, reboot all nodes. In case you have some storage
	 nodes that export a global file-system (e.g. <firstterm>NFS</firstterm> or
	 <firstterm>Lustre</firstterm>), reboot them first, then all the other nodes.
       </para>
       <para>
	 If the update doesn't contain a new kernel, you have the choice of either rebooting
	 the nodes like above or using the <application>Qlustar online update
	 mechanism</application> (currently the online update has to be executed manually,
	 future versions of <application>QluMan</application> will allow to do this from the
	 GUI) as follows: Execute the following command on the head-node:
       </para>
       <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
qlustar-image-update -H &lt;hostlist&gt;</command>
       </screen>
       <para>
	 where &lt;hostlist&gt; is a list of nodes in hostlist format, e.g. beo-[01-80]. You
	 also have the option to first check what exactly the update will change. To find out,
	 execute the following:
       </para>
       <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
qlustar-image-update -c -H &lt;hostlist&gt;</command>
       </screen>
       <para>
	 This will show what will be changed by this update.
       </para>
       <screen>
<prompt>0 root@cl-head ~ #</prompt><command>
qlustar-image-update -s -H &lt;hostlist&gt;</command>
       </screen>
       <para>
	 This will show all services (daemons) that need to be restarted as a result of this
	 update. If you want more detailed information about the update process, add the option
	 <emphasis>-v</emphasis> to any of the previous command lines.
       </para>
       <section xml:id="image-update">
	 <title>When will images be updated/rebuilt?</title>
	 <para>
	   There are a couple of cases to distinguish, depending on what version is selected
	   for an image in QluMan (see also the corresponding section in the <link
	   xlink:href="../QluMan_Guide/index.html#sec-Qlustar-OS-Images___blank___">QluMan
	   Guide</link>
	 </para>
	 <orderedlist>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       Selected image version is of <type>type x.y.z</type>, e.g. 11.0.0. In
	       this case, the image will be rebuilt if and only if there is an update for the
	       selected version (11.0.0) of the modules. Such updates will always be
	       bug-/security-fixes.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       Selected image version is of <type>type x.y</type>, e.g. 11.0 with 11.0.0 being
	       the most recent 11.0.z version before applying the update. In this case the
	       image is rebuilt, if the update entails a new maintenance release (e.g. 11.0.1
	       which will then become the new real image version) or an update for the
	       currently installed (11.0.0) modules.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       Selected image version is of <type>type x</type>, e.g. 11 with 11.0 being the
	       most recent 11.y and 11.0.0 being the most recent 11.0.z version before applying
	       the update. In this case the image is rebuilt, if either the update entails a
	       new feature release (e.g. 11.1, the latest 11.1.z will then become the new real
	       image version) or a new maintenance release (e.g. 11.0.1 which will then become
	       the new real image version) or an update for the currently installed (11.0.0)
	       modules. With this option, manual intervention to obtain a new image version is
	       only necessary when upgrading to a new major release (e.g. 11.y.z).
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
	 </orderedlist>
       </section>
     </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
