<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-Adding-Hosts">
  <title>Adding/Configuring Hosts</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Adding-Hosts">
    <title>Adding Hosts</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The New Hosts Window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The New Hosts Window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To add new hosts to the cluster you can either select "New Hosts" from the context menu
      in the Enclosure View tree or from the "Manage Hosts" menu. This opens the "Hosts
      Window".
    </para>
    <para>
      Adding a new host requires the specification of an IP address, hostname and MAC in the
      corresponding three text fields of the dialog. The entered values are checked for their
      validity. If one of them is not valid, the check-box to its right remains cleared.  The
      tool-tip of the check-box will then show, why it is invalid. If all the values are valid,
      all check-boxes will show a solid check and the <guibutton>Add Host</guibutton> button
      will become selectable.
    </para>
    <para>
      For convenience and if it makes sense, the IP address and the numeric part of the
      hostname (if there is one) will automatically be incremented by one, after a host was
      added. So in most cases, these fields will not have to be changed manually to add the
      next host. Only the new MAC will need to be entered.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-select.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Table of unknown MACs
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Table of unknown MACs
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To help adding new hosts, qlumand scans the <filename>DHCP log file</filename> for
      unknown hosts that have requested an IP address. For each unknown host found in the
      logs, the table at the top of the window shows the time of the first and last
      appearance in the log, its MAC address as well as the hardware vendor this MAC is
      assigned too (if known). Selecting a MAC in the table copies it into the MAC text field
      at the bottom and a double-click adds the host with the selected MAC. One can also
      select multiple lines (by holding the <keycap>CTRL</keycap> key and clicking or holding
      the <keycap>shift</keycap> key and dragging the mouse) and then click the
      <guibutton>Add Selected</guibutton> button at the bottom to add them all using the
      auto-increment feature for the IP address and hostname. If unsure, try adding a single
      host first and check the auto-increment does the right thing before adding a group of
      hosts.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-template.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a template for new hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a template for new hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-copy_host.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Select host to copy settings from
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Select host to copy settings from
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-copy_host2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Copy settings to new hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Copy settings to new hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      One easy way to add groups of hosts is to power them on one at a time with a
      short delay (say 30 seconds). The hosts will then appear in the Unknown MACs table in
      the order they were powered on and can be added as a group with the click of a single
      button.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the bottom of the window a <link linkend="Host-Templates">Host Template</link>
      can be selected that will be used as the default for new hosts. Most of the time, no
      additional configuration is needed for a new host. As an alternative way to make settings
      for the new hosts, one can select an existing properly configured host and choose to copy
      its settings to the new ones.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Configuring-Hosts">
    <title>Configuring Hosts</title>
    <section xml:id="sec-Levels-of-Configuration">
      <title>Four Levels of configuration</title>
      <para>
        The configuration of a host results from the assignment of different types of
        properties and <literal>Config Classes</literal> to it. A property is always a key +
        value pair. They are further divided into <literal>Generic Properties</literal> and
        <literal>Hardware Properties</literal>. Generic/hardware properties and config classes
        can be individually assigned to a host. This is the configuration level with highest
        priority, meaning that such an assignment will always be effective.
      </para>
      <para>
        They can also be used to define <literal>Generic Property Sets</literal>,
        <literal>Hardware Property Sets</literal> and <literal>Config Sets</literal>. This is
        simply a means of grouping them together, so they can be used as a single entity. These
        sets may also be individually assigned to a host. This is the configuration level with
        second highest priority.
      </para>
      <para>
        The third level of configuration are <literal>Host Templates</literal>. A Host
        Template consists of exactly one <literal>Config Set</literal>, one <literal>Generic
        Property Set</literal> and one <literal>Hardware Property Set</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The fourth and most generic level of configuration is the <literal>Global
        Template</literal>. It applies to all hosts in the cluster and consists of the
        <literal>Global</literal> Generic/Hardware Property and Config Set. In principle,
        the latter are just like any other set, with the one difference that they always
        apply to all hosts. This is useful when defining a base configuration for a cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/enclosure_view/properties_and_configs.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Overwritten properties/configs.
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Overwritten properties/configs.
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        If a generic/hardware property or config is defined and assigned to a host in a
        particular hierarchy level, it overwrites the corresponding assignment(s)/value(s) from
        all lower priority levels. This introduces a lot of flexibility while retaining
        consistency.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example it allows setting a property in the Global Template that is right for most
        hosts and then replace it in a particular Host Template being used for a few
        exceptional hosts. The screen-shot shows two examples of this strategy: The assigned
        Host Template of the chosen host replaces the configs for <literal>Net
        Config</literal>, <literal>Slurm Partition</literal> and <literal>Slurm Node
        Group</literal> of the Global Template (red box) and the number of CPU cores is
        directly assigned replacing the value from the Host Template (green box).
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
	  The tree representation of a host's properties/configs in the Enclosure View clearly
	  indicates overwritten assignments by displaying them in a light gray.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-properties">
      <title>Generic and Hardware Properties</title>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Hardware-Properties">Hardware Properties</bridgehead>
      <para>
        <literal>Hardware Properties</literal> are used to describe the hardware of a
        host. Among others, hardware properties like the amount of RAM or number of CPU cores
        are used to configure the Slurm workload manager, so jobs can be assigned to the
        desired hosts. Others, like e.g. the HW type, are purely informational and might be
        used for inventory management.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_host.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Detected Hardware Properties
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Detected Hardware Properties
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <literal>Hardware Properties</literal> usually don't have to be entered by hand. When a
        host boots, the basic hardware properties are detected and reported to the server.
        They are shown as a tool-tip in the <literal>Enclosure View</literal> when hovering
        over a host. The <link linkend="chap-HWwizard">Hardware Wizard</link> uses the reported
        values to create the correct configuration for a set of hosts and is the best way to
        create their initial configuration. It can also be used to correct the configuration of
        hosts in case their hardware was changed.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Generic-Properties">Generic Properties</bridgehead>
      <para>
        A property that is not hardware related is called generic. <literal>Generic
        Properties</literal> can be configuration options, like <parameter>OpenSM
        Host</parameter>, or purely informational, like <parameter>Paid by</parameter>. While
        hardware properties are meant to be more rigid, typically with a configurable set of
        fixed values, generic properties are more flexible and can be defined at
        will. <literal>Generic Properties</literal> are also not necessarily unique, making it
        possible to assign multiple values for a single generic property. This is useful
        e.g. to put hosts in multiple groups for dsh/pdsh (via the 'Host tag').
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/generic_property_set/edit-properties.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Editing Properties
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Editing Properties
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/hardware_property_set/property-editor.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Property Editor
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Property Editor
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/hardware_property_set/new-property.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Creating a new Property
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Creating a new Property
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        Generic/Hardware properties and their values are managed by the corresponding
        <literal>Property Editor</literal>. It is reachable from the Generic/Hardware Property
        Sets windows.  A new Generic/Hardware property can be created by clicking the
        <guibutton>New</guibutton> button. Each property has a name and a description. The name
        must be unique and the <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> button will only be enabled if that is
        the case. The description is optional and will be shown as a tool-tip when hovering
        over the property in other windows.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/hardware_property_set/property-editor-select.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Select Property
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Select Property
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/hardware_property_set/property-editor-context-menu.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Add property value
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Add property value
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        Once a property exists, values can be added to it. To accomplish this, the property
        must first be selected from the drop-down menu at the top of the Property Editor. Then
        values may be added or deleted using the context-menu.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/hardware_property_set/property-editor-edit-name.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Editing name of property
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Editing name of property
          </para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
        With the exception of essential pre-defined properties, a property can be
        edited by clicking the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. Examples of properties that
        can not be edited (or deleted) are the ones used to generate the
        <literal>slurm.conf</literal>. Changing their name would lead to errors in the
        generated file. Similarly, some property values can not be deleted and will be shown
        grayed out.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-PropConf-Sets">
      <title>Property/Config Sets</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/hardware_property_set/hardware-prop-sets.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Hardware Property Sets
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Hardware Property Sets
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/generic_property_set/generic-prop-sets.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Generic Property Sets
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Generic Property Sets
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/config_set/config-sets.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Config Sets
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Config Sets
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Generic/hardware sets and config sets simplify the configuration of hosts
	substantially. They are a means of grouping generic/hardware properties or configs, so
	they can be used as a single entity and be assigned to individual hosts directly or via
	a <literal>Host Template</literal>. There is also a global set of each type which is
	always assigned to <emphasis>every</emphasis> host. The generic/hardware and config
	sets can be managed by opening the corresponding window from the <guimenuitem>Manage
	Sets</guimenuitem> menu.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Hardware-Generic-Property-Sets">Hardware/Generic Property Sets</bridgehead>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/hardware_property_set/hardware-prop-sets-new.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    New Property Set
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    New Property Set
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/hardware_property_set/hardware-prop-sets-new2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    New Property Set dialog
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    New Property Set dialog
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Property sets are shown in tree form with the name of each set as the top level item
	and the key/value pairs of assigned properties as children. The first entry is always
	the global property set. A new property set can be created by clicking the
	<guibutton>New</guibutton> button or from the context menu. An existing property set
	can be renamed or the description changed by selecting <guimenuitem>Edit Property
	Set</guimenuitem> from the context menu. Deletion of an unused property set is also
	possible via the context menu.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/hardware_property_set/hardware-prop-set-add-prop.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Add Property to Set
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Add Property to Set
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	New properties can be added to a property set by opening the <guimenuitem>Add
	Property</guimenuitem> sub-menu in the context menu: Select the desired property and
	its value. Only properties and values that don't conflict with already included
	properties or values are shown in the sub-menu. Already included properties may be
	changed in two ways: Either a different value is selected from the drop-down menu or
	the value is edited directly, in which case the change must be confirmed by pressing
	<keycap>return</keycap>. If the entered value for the property doesn't exist yet, a new
	value is automatically created. Another way to create new values and the only way to
	delete them is through the <link linkend="Generic-Properties">property editor</link> by
	clicking <guibutton>Edit Properties</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Config-Sets">Config Sets</bridgehead>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/config_set/config-set-add-config.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Add Config Class to Set
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Add Config Class to Set
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Config sets are managed the same way as property sets. They are displayed as a tree
	with the global set at the top and the key/value pairs of assigned config classes as
	children. Creating a new config set can be done by clicking the
	<guibutton>New</guibutton> button or from the context menu just like for property
	sets. Adding and removing config classes to/from a set also works the same way.
      </para>
      <para>
	Unlike property sets though, the list of usable config classes is fixed and values can
	not be edited directly from this window. <link linkend="chap-Config-Classes">Config
	classes</link> require a more complex and individual config. So for each config class
	there is a menu item in the <guimenuitem>Manage Configs</guimenuitem> menu. Depending
	on the type of config class, one or more values for that class can be assigned to a
	<literal>Config Set</literal> (slurm partitions are an example where multiple values
	are assignable).
	<note>
	  <para>
	    The sub-menu only shows config classes and values that can be added without
	    conflicting with already assigned entries.
	  </para>
	</note>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-Assigning-Config">
      <title>Assigning a configuration to hosts</title>
      <para>
      As mentioned in the beginning of this chapter there are 4 levels of configuration. Going
      from lowest to highest priority these are: <literal>Global Template</literal>,
      <literal>Host Template</literal>, directly assigned sets and directly assigned properties
      and configs.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Global-Template">Global Template</bridgehead>
      <para>
	The <literal>Global Template</literal> is the most generic way to assign configurations
	to hosts. It applies to all hosts in the cluster and consists of the
	<literal>Global</literal> Generic/Hardware Property and Config Set.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="Host-Templates">Host Templates</bridgehead>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_template.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Selecting a Host Template
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Selecting a Host Template
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_template2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Selecting a Host Template for multiple hosts
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Selecting a Host Template for multiple hosts
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	The next level of configuration is the <literal>Host Template</literal>. When a correct
	<literal>Host Template</literal> exists, a host can be configured by selecting the
	desired template in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> window. For a single
	host, this can be done by selecting it in the tree view. This brings up the host
	information on the right and a template can be selected from the drop-down menu. To
	configure multiple hosts, you would select them in the tree view and choose a
	<literal>Host Template</literal> from the context menu. The check-marks in the sub-menu
	indicate which <literal>Host Templates</literal> are currently assigned (if any) for
	the selected nodes. This action will override the previous assignment for all selected
	hosts.
      </para>
      <para>
	Alternatively, especially when no correct <literal>Host Template</literal> exists yet,
	the <link linkend="chap-HWwizard">Hardware Wizard</link> can be used to to create a new
	or modify an existing <literal>Host Template</literal> and assign it to hosts.
      </para>
      <bridgehead xml:id="x2host-mapping">Directly assigned properties, configs and sets</bridgehead>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_generic_property.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Selecting a Generic Property
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Selecting a Generic Property
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Generic/hardware properties, configs and their corresponding sets can also be
	individually assigned to a host. Such assigned properties take precedence over ones of
	the same type selected through the Host or Global Template. This is useful when a
	particular (or a few) node(s) require a special property/config (set) while everything
	else should be set the same as for other hosts with the same template.
      </para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  By default, every new host has the generic property <parameter>Schedule Format:
	  always</parameter>, which is required to format the disk on the first boot. This
	  property should be removed (or changed to <literal>never</literal>) after the first
	  successful boot of the host, so that log files will be preserved across boots in the
	  future.
	</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
