<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-Adding-Hosts">
  <title>Adding/Configuring Hosts</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Adding-Hosts">
    <title>Adding Hosts</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The New Hosts Window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The New Hosts Window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To add new hosts to the cluster you can either select "New Hosts" from the context menu
      in the Enclosure View tree or from the "Manage Hosts" menu. This opens the "Hosts
      Window".
    </para>
    <para>
      Adding a new host requires the specification of an IP address, hostname and MAC in the
      corresponding three text fields of the dialog. The entered values are checked for their
      validity. If one of them is not valid, the check-box to its right remains cleared.  The
      tool-tip of the check-box will then show, why it is invalid. If all the values are valid,
      all check-boxes will show a solid check and the <guibutton>Add Host</guibutton> button
      will become selectable.
    </para>
    <para>
      For convenience and if it makes sense, the IP address and the numeric part of the
      hostname (if there is one) will automatically be incremented by one, after a host was
      added. So in most cases, these fields will not have to be changed manually to add the
      next host. Only the new MAC will need to be entered.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-select.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Table of unknown MACs
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Table of unknown MACs
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To help adding new hosts, qlumand scans the <filename>DHCP log file</filename> for
      unknown hosts that have requested an IP address. For each unknown host found in the
      logs, the table at the top of the window shows the time of the first and last
      appearance in the log, its MAC address as well as the hardware vendor this MAC is
      assigned too (if known). Selecting a MAC in the table copies it into the MAC text field
      at the bottom and a double-click adds the host with the selected MAC. One can also
      select multiple lines (by holding the <keycap>CTRL</keycap> key and clicking or holding
      the <keycap>shift</keycap> key and dragging the mouse) and then click the
      <guibutton>Add Selected</guibutton> button at the bottom to add them all using the
      auto-increment feature for the IP address and hostname. If unsure, try adding a single
      host first and check the auto-increment does the right thing before adding a group of
      hosts.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-template.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a template for new hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a template for new hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-copy_host.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Select host to copy settings from
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Select host to copy settings from
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/new_host/window-copy_host2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Copy settings to new hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Copy settings to new hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      One easy way to add groups of hosts is to power them on one at a time with a
      short delay (say 30 seconds). The hosts will then appear in the Unknown MACs table in
      the order they were powered on and can be added as a group with the click of a single
      button.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the bottom of the window a <link linkend="Host-Templates">Host Template</link>
      can be selected that will be used as the default for new hosts. Most of the time, no
      additional configuration is needed for a new host. As an alternative way to make settings
      for the new hosts, one can select an existing properly configured host and choose to copy
      its settings to the new ones.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Configuring-Hosts">
    <title>Configuring Hosts</title>
    <para>
      The configuration of a host consists of the definition and assignment of different
      types of properties and config classes. Properties are always a key + value pair and
      are further split into generic, hardware and specific properties.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="Hardware-Properties">Hardware Properties</bridgehead>
    <para>
      <literal>Hardware properties</literal> are used to describe the hardware of a
      host. Amongst others, hardware properties like the amount of RAM or number of CPU cores
      are used to configure resource management systems like slurm or torque, so jobs can be
      assigned to the desired hosts. Others, like e.g. the server model or BIOS version, are
      purely informational and might be used for inventory management.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="Generic-Properties">Generic Properties</bridgehead>
    <para>
      A property that is not hardware related and not specific to a host is called generic.
      <literal>Generic properties</literal> can be configuration options, like
      <parameter>OpenSM Host</parameter>, or purely informational, like <parameter>Paid
      by</parameter>. While hardware properties are meant to be more rigid, typically with a
      configurable set of fixed values, generic properties are more flexible and can be defined
      at will. This will become more apparent in future versions of
      <application>QluMan</application>. <literal>Generic properties</literal> are also not
      necessarily unique, making it possible to assign multiple values for a single generic
      property. This is useful e.g. to add multiple torque host tags or to put hosts in
      multiple groups for dsh/pdsh (via the 'Host tag').
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="Specific-Properties">Specific Properties</bridgehead>
    <para>
      As the name suggests, <literal>specific properties</literal> are specific to a single
      host. The best example for such a property is the serial number of the host.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="PropConf-Sets">Property/Config Sets</bridgehead>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_template.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a Host Template
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a Host Template
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Individual generic properties, hardware properties and config classes can be used to
      define generic property sets, hardware property sets and config sets. This is simply a
      means of grouping them together so they can be used as a single entity. A <literal>Host
      Template</literal> can then be created by choosing one generic property set, one
      hardware property set and one config set.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="Host-Templates">Host Templates</bridgehead>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_template2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a Host Template for multiple hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a Host Template for multiple hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      When a correct <literal>Host Template</literal> exists, a host can be configured by
      selecting the desired template in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> window.  For
      a single host, this can be done by selecting it in the tree view. This brings up the host
      information on the right and a template can be selected from the drop-down menu. To
      configure multiple hosts, you would select them in the tree view and choose a
      <literal>Host Template</literal> from the context menu. The check-marks in the sub-menu
      indicate which <literal>Host Templates</literal> are currently assigned (if any) for the
      selected nodes. This action will override the previous assignment.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="Global-Template">Global Template</bridgehead>
    <para>
    Even more generic is the <literal>Global Template</literal>. The <literal>Global
    Template</literal> applies to all hosts in the cluster and consists of the <literal>Global
    Generic Property Set</literal>, the <literal>Global Hardware Property Set</literal> and
    the <literal>Global Config Set</literal>. These are just like any other set, a simple means
    of grouping individual generic properties, hardware properties and config classes, with
    the one difference that they always apply to all hosts as a base configuration.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="x2host-mapping">Directly assigned properties, configs and sets</bridgehead>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_generic_property.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a Generic Property
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a Generic Property
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <literal>Generic properties</literal>, <literal>hardware properties</literal>,
      <literal>config sets</literal> and their corresponding sets can also be assigned to a
      host individually. Such
      assigned properties take precedence over ones of the same type selected through the
      <literal>Host Template</literal>. This is useful when a property should be changed
      temporarily for some hosts or when a property should not be
      changeable globally through the Host Template. Note that by default, every new host has
      the generic property <parameter>Schedule Format: always</parameter>, which is required
      to format the disk on the first boot. This should be removed after the first successful
      boot of the host, so that log files will be preserved across boots in the future.
    </para>
    <bridgehead xml:id="levels-of-configuration">4 Levels of configuration</bridgehead>
    <para>
      Overall the configuration of a host is composed of the 4 levels of configuration
      described above. Going from lowest to highest priority these are: <literal>Global
      Template</literal>, <literal>Host Template</literal>, directly assigned sets and
      directly assigned properties and configs.
    </para>
    <para>
      <!--cbox(file: enclosure_view/properties_and_configs.png caption: )-->
      In each level if a generic property, hardware property or config is set then it
      replaces the value or values from all lower levels. This allows for example setting a
      property that is right for most hosts in the Global Template and then replace it in
      a specific Host Template used for the few exceptions. The screenshot shows 2 examples.
      The Host Template replaces the configs for NetConfigName, SlurmPartitionName and
      SlurmGroupName of the Global Template (red box) and the number of CPU cores is directly
      assigned replacing the value from the Host Template (green box).
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
