<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-Enclosures">
  <title>Enclosures</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Enclosure-View">
    <title>Enclosure View</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/startup.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The Enclosure View
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The Enclosure View
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      The <classname>Enclosure View</classname> shows an overview of the cluster in a tree
      structure.  The tree structure is designed to reflect the physical structure of the
      cluster. At the lowest level are the hosts. A host can be a head, storage or compute
      node but also a switch e.g. In general, anything in the cluster that has a name, IP and
      MAC address is a host. A host is represented by its <literal>bare board</literal> and
      should be placed into a <firstterm> host enclosure</firstterm>. 1U, 2U, 3U or 4U
      enclosures contain exactly one board, while others like a Twin or Blade chassis can
      have multiple boards. Once defined, host enclosures can be placed into
      <firstterm>racks</firstterm>, racks grouped into rows, rows into rooms and so on. The
      tree has a simple drag&amp;drop interface. E.g. you can select a number of nodes (by
      holding the <keycap>CTRL</keycap> key and clicking or holding the <keycap>shift
      key</keycap> and dragging the mouse) and drag&amp;drop them into a <firstterm>Blade
      enclosure</firstterm>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_host.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selected host in Enclosure View
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selected host in Enclosure View
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Selecting a node in the tree displays its configuration info on the right hand side:
      The hostname, IP and MAC can be edited and saved by pressing
      <keycap>return</keycap>. The check-mark to the right of the field shows the state of
      the change. If the entered value is not valid, the check-box is cleared
    </para>
    <para>
      The check-boxes tool-tip (you'll see it when the mouse moves on top of it) gives the
      reason, why the entered value is invalid. If the entered value is valid but has not yet
      been saved, the check-box is checked but ghosted. Finally, after the value has been
      saved in the database, the check-box shows a solid check.
    </para>
    <para>
      For nodes that are not part of a <literal>multi-host enclosure</literal> (like a Blade
      or Twin chassis) the enclosure type can be changed to one of the single-slot host
      enclosures (1U, 2U, etc.). A new enclosure of the chosen type will then be created if
      the node is not already part of one. If a node is included in a multi-host enclosure,
      this field will be ghosted.
    </para>
    <para>
      The template field allows to select a so-called <link linkend="Host-Templates">Host
      Template</link> for the node. Usually, large groups of nodes have an identical hardware
      and software configuration and will use the same template. Deviations from the properties
      coming from the template can be set for individual hosts by direct assignment of either a
      property/config set or individual properties/configs directly to the host through its
      context menu. In case of unique properties, direct assignments override settings from the
      template (or property set), for non-unique properties this is additive.
      <note>
	<para>
	  Any changes made in the configuration only affect the active node (as indicated by
	  the hostname in the info part of the enclosure view), and not all selected
	  nodes. Configurations for all selected nodes can be made by using the context menu
	  (right click) in the tree view.
	</para>
      </note>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Managing-Enclosures">
    <title>Managing Enclosures</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_twin2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Showing the enclosure layout
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Showing the enclosure layout
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Similar to host nodes, selecting an enclosure entry displays the physical layout of the
      corresponding enclosure on the right. Controls to select the visibility level and
      special slots are available at the top of the display. See below for more details about
      these. The name of the enclosure and its type (in brackets) is shown in the title. In
      the above case, both name and type are "Twin². Below the title you have a
      representation of the physical layout of the enclosure. For this example, you see the
      2x2 slots that are characteristic of a
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_rack_specials.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Activate special rack slots
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Activate special rack slots
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Twin² enclosure. Two slots are filled with <systemitem
      class="systemname">beo-01</systemitem> and <systemitem
      class="systemname">beo-02</systemitem> and two slots remain empty, showing only the
      number of each slot in brackets.
    </para>
    <para>
      Selecting a rack shows a more complex picture. The current example rack holds ten
      enclosures in its central 19 inch slots: A FatTwin, a Twin, a Twin², a Blade 1, 3 Blade
      2, another Twin² and two 1U enclosures containing <systemitem
      class="systemname">beo-11</systemitem> and <systemitem
      class="systemname">beo-12</systemitem>. The special top, left, right and bottom (not
      visible) slots are empty. In future versions a network switch or power controller, that
      is mounted at some special position of the rack, can be placed into these special
      slots.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_rack.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          A rack with one visible level
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          A rack with one visible level
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_rack_deep.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
           A rack with two visible levels
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
           A rack with two visible levels
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Now let's explain the effect of the two controls at the top in more detail: The
      <guibutton>Show special slots</guibutton> check-box controls the visibility of the top,
      left, right and bottom special slots. Especially if these slots are empty, this will
      provide a more compact view of the interesting central slots. The other control, the
      visibility level, controls how many levels of the enclosure hierarchy are shown:
      Selecting a depth of 2 shows not only the selected rack with its slots but also the
      contents of the enclosures in each slot.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since the current version of <application>QluMan</application> only supports host
      enclosures (Twin, Blade, ...) and racks, a depth larger than 2 has no effect yet. In
      future versions, it will be possible to group racks into rows, rows into rooms, rooms
      into buildings and so on. This will allow you to reflect the physical layout of your
      cluster in as much detail, as you like.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sec-Populating-Enclosures">
      <title>Populating Enclosures</title>
      <para>
	New enclosures can be added through the context menu. The new enclosure must be given
	a name and its type can be selected. Currently, enclosure types cannot be manipulated
	yet. This will change in a future version.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/new_enclosure.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Adding new enclosures
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Adding new enclosures
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/new_enclosure2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    The New Enclosures Dialog
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    The New Enclosures Dialog
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Suitable for ordinary servers, a host being selected in the enclosure view can be
	placed into a single slot host enclosure directly by selecting the correct type in
	the host info part of the window (see <xref linkend="sec-Enclosure-View"/>). For host
	enclosures that can hold more than one server/node (twin servers, blades etc.),
	drag&amp;drop may be used to move hosts into them. Moreover, it's also possible to
	create larger (non-host) enclosures (like racks) and move host enclosures into them
	also by using using drag&amp;drop. Note, that a bare host cannot be placed directly
	into a non-host enclosure, only if it is already inside a host enclosure.
      </para>
      <para>
	Another option to place hosts into enclosures is by selecting a number of them and
	then choosing a host enclosure from the context menu. This way, a new enclosure of
	the selected type is automatically created and all selected hosts are moved into
	it. If more hosts than can fit into a single enclosure of the chosen type are
	selected, additional enclosures of the same type will be created such that all hosts
	can be placed into one of them. This makes it easy to position large numbers of
	identical hosts into their enclosures. If the selected hosts were in an enclosure
	before and that enclosure becomes empty and is not itself part of a larger enclosure
	then the empty enclosure is automatically removed.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_host_enclosure.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Placing hosts into an enclosure
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Placing hosts into an enclosure
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_host_enclosure2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Enclosure hosts
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Enclosure hosts
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Relocating hosts by selecting a different host enclosure is supported not only on
	directly selected hosts but also on hosts inside selected enclosures. This allows
	changing the type of enclosure a group of hosts is in by selecting the old
	enclosure(s) and choosing a new one from the context menu. Note that this procedure
	does not change the type of the old enclosure but rather creates a new one, moves all
	the hosts to it and then deletes the now empty old enclosure(s).
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/select_host_enclosure3.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Changing the type of an enclosure
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Changing the type of an enclosure
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Try it out: Place a number of hosts into a large enclosure (like a blade), then select
	the enclosure and choose a small enclosure (like 1U) to relocate them. In general, such
	an operation will create one enclosure of the new type and fill all its slots before
	creating a second one. Hosts having been in different enclosures before, can end up in
	the same enclosure and hosts that were in the same enclosure before can end up in
	different enclosures after this operation.
      </para>
      <para>
	When using drag&amp;drop for the relocation, the host or enclosure is always placed
	into the lowest suitable slot of the target enclosure. This reflects our experience,
	that usually enclosures are simply filled from left to right and bottom to top.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/enclosure_view/move_to_slot.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Moving to a different slot
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Moving to a different slot
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	But sometimes this is not the case and a host or enclosure should be in a different
	slot as compared to the automatic placement. In this case, the host or enclosure can be
	moved through the context menu. The latter shows all the free slots the host or
	enclosure can be relocated to and a checked mark indicates the current location. Of
	course the relocation is only allowed into free slots. Hence, it may require removing
	(drag&amp;drop out of the enclosure) a host or enclosure temporarily to free space for
	moving things around.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="sec-Host-Selections">
	<title>Host Selections</title>
	<para>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject><imagedata
	    fileref="images/enclosure_view/selection_button.png"
	    width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	    <textobject><phrase>
	      Alternative selection of hosts
	    </phrase></textobject>
	    <caption><para>
	      Alternative selection of hosts
	    </para></caption>
	  </mediaobject>
	  There are situations, where one wants to change a property or config of a whole set
	  of hosts. For example, you may want to change all nodes located in a particular blade
	  to no longer format their disk on boot. This can be achieved by selecting a set of
	  hosts in the enclosure view with the mouse. A range of hosts can be selected by
	  clicking on the first host and then clicking on the last host, while pressing the
	  shift key. Hosts can also be added or removed from the selection by clicking on a
	  host while pressing the <keycap>CTRL</keycap> key. Once a set of hosts is selected,
	  changes can be made to all selected hosts through the context menu. For instance,
	  this allows changing the Host Template or add/alter a generic property of a set of
	  hosts.
	</para>
	<note>
	  <para>
	    When a host is part of an enclosure, selecting the enclosure will also select the
	    host(s) inside of the enclosure, provided it is <emphasis
	    role="bold">collapsed</emphasis>. However, hosts inside of expanded enclosures must
	    be selected individually.
	  </para>
	</note>
	<para>
	  An alternative and more powerful way to select a set of hosts is available via the
	  <guibutton>Selection</guibutton> button at the bottom of the <classname>Enclosure
	  View</classname>. When pressed, at the top of the appearing selection menu you'll
	  find 3 items: To select all hosts, clear the selection or to invert the
	  selection.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject><imagedata
	    fileref="images/enclosure_view__selection/menu.png"
	    width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	    <textobject><phrase>
	      Different ways of selecting hosts
	    </phrase></textobject>
	    <caption><para>
	      Different ways of selecting hosts
	    </para></caption>
	  </mediaobject>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject><imagedata
	    fileref="images/enclosure_view__selection/submenu.png"
	    width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	    <textobject><phrase>
	      Different selection operators
	    </phrase></textobject>
	    <caption><para>
	      Different selection operators
	    </para></caption>
	  </mediaobject>
	  Below these items is a list of filters by which subsets of hosts were defined
	  according to specific criteria. For more details on how to construct such Host
	  Filters see <xref linkend="chap-Host-Filters"/>. When pressing
	  <guibutton>Select</guibutton>, the selection is set to the hosts defined by the
	  corresponding filter, dropping any previously selected hosts. <guibutton>Add
	  to</guibutton> adds, while <guibutton>Remove from</guibutton> removes the hosts
	  defined by the filter from the current selection. <guibutton>Intersection</guibutton>
	  sets the selection to only those hosts in the current selection, that are also part
	  of the set defined by the filter.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
