<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-HWwizard">
  <title>Hardware Wizard</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-purpose">
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <para>
      When setting up new hosts, there are a number of configuration or other settings to be
      made. They are used to specify their hardware configuration, to determine what OS they
      should boot and to fine-tune the behavior of applications running on them. All the
      necessary steps for the desired configuration of the nodes can be done manually and also
      be changed later through the various dialogs from the main window.
    </para>
    <para>
      As a convenient alternative, the <classname>Hardware Wizard</classname> guides you
      through the necessary configuration steps with a special emphasis on the hardware
      configuration. It uses the auto-detected hardware properties of hosts to suggest their
      optimal configuration options. Furthermore, it tries to keep a balance between the
      available configuration strategies: Using templates, property/config sets or individual
      properties/config classes.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-host-selection">
    <title>Selecting Hosts</title>
    <para>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject><imagedata
       fileref="images/hw_wizard/host_selection.png"
       width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>
         Selecting hosts for configuration
       </phrase></textobject>
       <caption><para>
         Selecting hosts for configuration
       </para></caption>
     </mediaobject>
      The first step is to select the hosts that should be configured . Initially, the lists of
      hosts is empty. One or more of the four buttons at the bottom have to be pressed to
      pre-select hosts that should be considered. The <guibutton>Unconfigured</guibutton>
      button adds all hosts that do not have any hardware configured at all. A freshly added
      host without an assigned <classname>Host Template</classname> will fall into this
      category. The <guibutton>Partially Configured</guibutton> button adds hosts that already
      have some hardware configured correctly but not all of it. The <guibutton>Wrongly
      Configured</guibutton> button adds hosts, where the configured hardware properties do not
      match the hardware detected at boot, e.g. when nodes have been updated with more
      ram. Finally, the <guibutton>Selected</guibutton> button adds hosts, that have been
      selected in the enclosure view, including hosts that are configured correctly already.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once one or more of the buttons are pressed, the affected hosts will show up in the
      table. To keep things compact, hosts with identically detected hardware are grouped
      together and shown in <emphasis>hostlist syntax</emphasis>. By default, all shown groups
      are selected and will be configured using a single <classname>Host Template</classname>
      and therefore single <classname>Hardware Property</classname>, <classname>Generic
      Property</classname> and <classname>Config Set</classname>. The possible differences in
      hardware configurations within the list of selected hosts will be handled by the wizard
      with the <emphasis>per host</emphasis> settings. In case all the groups shouldn't use the
      same <classname>Host Template</classname>, groups may be selected or deselected
      individually and the remaining ones can be configured by running the wizard again
      later. Groups of hosts with identical hardware can't be split up though. If this is
      required, select the hosts individually in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> and
      use only the <guibutton>Selected</guibutton> button. Once the desired groups of hosts
      have been selected click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to continue configuring them.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-template">
    <title>Configure Host Template</title>
    <para>
      The main configuration of hosts comes from the Host Template. This determines what
      Hardware Property Set, Generic Property Set and Config Set is used for each host. The
      wizard tries to find an existing Host Template that matches the hardware detected for at
      least some of the selected hosts. If it does this Host Template will be pre selected and
      the "Use existing Host Template" choice will be active.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/template-existing.png)-->
      The resulting configuration, if left unaltered, is shown below in tree form. The Hardware
      Properties in the Hardware Property Set for the Host Template are color coded to show how
      well they fit the groups of hosts being configured. Hovering over a Hardware property
      brings up a helpful tool-tip explaining the coloring.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/template-existing-tooltip.png)-->
      A green bulb means that the property matches the detected value for all hosts. A yellow
      bulb means that is matches some hosts but not all of them. This happens when hosts have
      different hardware and is acceptable. A red bulb means that the value matches none of the
      hosts and is a bad fit. The property value should be changed in the follow up pages or a
      different Host Template should be selected.
    </para>
    <para>
      The pre selected Host Template might not be the desired choice and a different one can be
      selected from the drop-down menu. The choices are colored showing how well a Host
      Template matches the hosts.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/template-existing-menu.png)-->
      Here a green bulb means that the Host Template matches the detected hardware of at least
      one host perfectly. A yellow bulb means that not all hardware for the hosts is configured
      but at least nothing is configured wrong. A red bulb means the Host Template includes a
      hardware property that matches none of the hosts and would be a bad fit. None the less it
      can be the right choice and it can be modified to fit in the followup page or the correct
      hardware properties can be set on a per host basis by the wizard.
    </para>
    <para>
      If none of the existing Host Templates are suitable then a new Host Template can be
      created in one of two ways. An existing Host Template can be cloned or a completely new
      Host Template can be created.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/template-clone.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/template-new.png)-->
      In both cases a name for the new Host Template must be given. The difference in the 2
      choices is that clone will pre select the Hardware Property Set, Generic Property Set and
      Config Set of the existing Host Template for use in the new one.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-hw-prop-set">
    <title>Select Hardware Property Set</title>
    <para>
      This page selects the Hardware Property Set used in the selected Host Template and is the
      main source for hardware configuration. Like in the previous page an existing Hardware
      Property Set can be used, can be cloned or a new Hardware Property Set can be
      created. Most likely an existing Hardware Property Set will be pre selected. A different
      existing Hardware Property Set can be selected from the drop-down menu and again the
      choices are color coded for how well they fit the hosts.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-menu.png)-->
      Changing the Hardware Property Set affects the selected Host Template. If an existing
      Host Template was chosen in the last page then changing it might affect hosts other than
      the ones being configured in the wizard. In such a case the wizard will ask for
      confirmation that that is desired.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-modify_template.png)-->
      The existing Hardware Property Set can be replaced with the auto-detected Hardware
      Properties on the bottom right for a better fit. If multiple groups of hosts are being
      configured at the same time the properties where hosts differ will have a drop-down menu
      to select the most suitable value.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-select_hw_prop.png)-->
      Once the right selection is made the properties can be copied over the existing Hardware
      Property Set by clicking the &lt;&lt; button. The wizard will ask for confirmation if
      this impacts hosts not currently being configured and then set the Hardware Property Set
      on the bottom left into edit mode, same as it is when cloning or creating a new Hardware
      Property Set.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-copied.png)-->
      The difference between cloning an existing Hardware Property Set and creating a new one
      is just what Hardware Properties are pre selected. Cloning will start with the properties
      the cloned set has while creating a new one start with a blank slate.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-clone.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new.png)-->
      In all 3 cases the Hardware Property Set can be further edited by selecting different
      values for properties, adding properties or removing properties.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new-add_property.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new-remove_property.png)-->
      Once the right Hardware Properties are selected click Next to continue.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-resolve-conflict">
    <title>Resolve Hardware Conflict</title>
    <para>
      If more than one group of hosts is being configured at the same time or when the selected
      Hardware Property Set is insufficient to correctly configure the hosts then the Resolve
      Hardware Conflict page comes next. At the bottom the conflicting or missing hardware
      properties are listed showing the correct value for each group. If only one property is
      missing then the wizard will suggest to add the property individually per host.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/resolve_hardware_conflict.png)-->
      On the other hand if multiple properties are missing adding a Hardware Property Set per
      host might be a better way and will be pre selected.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/resolve_hardware_conflict-sets.png)-->
      Which option is chosen is a matter of taste and there is no wrong choice here. One can
      also choose "configure manually later" to tell the wizard to ignore the conflict. Note
      that this will result in hosts that are only partially or wrongly configured which will
      need to be corrected later.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-per-host-hw-prop-set">
    <title>Additional per Host Hardware Property Set</title>
    <para>
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/per_host_hw_prop_set.png)-->
      If per host Hardware Property Sets was chosen in the previous page then the set to be
      used for each group will be picked here.
      The Wizard will look for an existing Hardware Property Set for each group that contains
      the right Hardware Properties already. If one is found it will be pre selected. Otherwise
      a name for a new set must be entered before one can continue.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-gen-prop-set">
    <title>Select Generic Property Set / Select Config Set</title>
    <para>
      To complete the Host Template a Generic Property Set and Config Set must be selected. The
      two pages are very much alike and similar to selecting the Hardware Property Set. Again
      there are 3 main options: Use existing set, clone existing set and new empty set. Since
      there is no auto-detection for the values in each set there is no color coding of the
      choices.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/gen_prop_set.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/config_set.png)-->
      An existing set can not be modified in the current version but when clone existing set or
      new empty set is chosen then properties and configs can be added to or removed from the
      set.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/gen_prop_set-add_property.png)-->
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/config_set-add_property.png)-->
      In the Select Generic Property Set page if the hosts have IPMI then the IPMI properties
      deserve consideration. In the Select Config Set page the Boot Config, Disk Config and
      UnionFS Chroot configs are usually set.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>
      This is the last page of the wizard and the final confirmation of all the choices made
      before the data is actually stored in the database.
      At the top the common configuration for all host from the Host Template is shown in tree
      form. At the bottom the additional Hardware Properties or Hardware Property Sets that
      will be set for each group of hosts on a per host basis to override the host template is
      shown. Host groups with no per host overrides are not shown.
      <!--cbox(file: hw_wizard/summary.png)-->
    </para>
    <para>
      If an existing Host Template or existing Hardware Property Set was modified then this is
      the last chance to not save that change. By clicking Finish all the modifications are
      made and the configuration is assigned to all hosts. The hosts should then be fully
      configured and ready to boot.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
