<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-HWwizard">
  <title>Hardware Wizard</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-purpose">
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <para>
      When setting up new hosts, there are a number of configuration or other settings to be
      made. They are used to specify their hardware configuration, to determine what OS they
      should boot and to fine-tune the behavior of applications running on them. All the
      necessary steps for the desired configuration of the nodes can be done manually and also
      be changed later through the various dialogs from the main window.
    </para>
    <para>
      As a convenient alternative, the <classname>Hardware Wizard</classname> guides you
      through the necessary configuration steps with a special emphasis on the hardware
      configuration. It uses the auto-detected hardware properties of hosts to suggest their
      optimal configuration options. Furthermore, it tries to keep a balance between the
      available configuration strategies: Using templates, property/config sets or individual
      properties/config classes.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-host-selection">
    <title>Selecting Hosts</title>
    <para>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject><imagedata
       fileref="images/hw_wizard/host_selection.png"
       width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>
         Selecting hosts for configuration
       </phrase></textobject>
       <caption><para>
         Selecting hosts for configuration
       </para></caption>
     </mediaobject>
      The first step is to select the hosts that should be configured. Initially, the lists of
      hosts is empty. One or more of the four buttons at the bottom have to be pressed to
      pre-select hosts that should be considered. The <guibutton>Unconfigured</guibutton>
      button adds all hosts that do not have any hardware configured at all. A freshly added
      host without an assigned <classname>Host Template</classname> will fall into this
      category. The <guibutton>Partially Configured</guibutton> button adds hosts that already
      have some hardware configured correctly but not all of it. The <guibutton>Wrongly
      Configured</guibutton> button adds hosts, where the configured hardware properties do not
      match the hardware detected at boot, e.g. when nodes have been updated with more
      ram. Finally, the <guibutton>Selected</guibutton> button adds hosts, that have been
      selected in the enclosure view, including hosts that are configured correctly already.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once one or more of the buttons are pressed, the affected hosts will show up in the
      table. To keep things compact, hosts with identically detected hardware are grouped
      together and shown in <emphasis>hostlist syntax</emphasis>. By default, all shown groups
      are selected and will be configured using a single <classname>Host Template</classname>
      and therefore single <classname>Hardware Property</classname>, <classname>Generic
      Property</classname> and <classname>Config Set</classname>. The possible differences in
      hardware configurations within the list of selected hosts will be handled by the wizard
      with the <emphasis>per host</emphasis> settings. In case all the groups shouldn't use the
      same <classname>Host Template</classname>, groups may be selected or deselected
      individually and the remaining ones can be configured by running the wizard again
      later. Groups of hosts with identical hardware can't be split up though. If this is
      required, select the hosts individually in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> and
      use only the <guibutton>Selected</guibutton> button. Once the desired groups of hosts
      have been selected click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to continue configuring them.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-template">
    <title>Configuring the Host Template</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/template-existing.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          A well matching Hardware Property set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          A well matching Hardware Property set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      As explained in <xref linkend="sec-Configuring-Hosts"/> the major part of a hosts
      configuration is derived from a <classname>Host Template</classname>. One of the wizard's
      goals is, to find an existing <classname>Host Template</classname> with a
      <classname>Hardware Property set</classname> that optimally matches the detected hardware
      for at least some of the selected hosts. If such a <classname>Host Template</classname>
      is found, it will be pre-selected and the <guibutton>Use existing Host
      Template</guibutton> choice will be active.
    </para>
    <para>
      The settings inherited from this template, are shown underneath in tree format and below
      the property tree, a list of hosts, that currently use the selected template, is shown
      for informational purpose.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/template-existing-tooltip.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Tool-tip explaining the coloring
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Tool-tip explaining the coloring
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      The individual properties belonging to the <classname>Hardware Property Set</classname>
      of the selected <classname>Host Template</classname> are color-coded, to show how well
      they fit the detected values of the host groups being configured. Hovering over a
      hardware property brings up a helpful tool-tip explaining the coloring.
      A green bulb indicates, that the property matches the detected value for all hosts. A
      yellow one, that it matches some but not all hosts. This happens, when some of the
      selected hosts have different hardware and means that the selected template is still a
      good fit. A red bulb indicates that the value matches none of the hosts and is a bad
      fit. Such a property value may be changed later in the follow-up pages or a different
      <classname>Host Template</classname> can be selected right-away.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/template-existing-menu.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Choosing alternative Host Templates
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Choosing alternative Host Templates
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      In case the pre-selected <classname>Host Template</classname> is not the desired choice,
      a different one can be selected from the drop-down menu. The choices are again
      color-coded to indicate how well they match the detected properties of the selected
      hosts. Here a green bulb means that the <classname>Host Template</classname> matches the
      detected hardware of at least one host perfectly. A yellow one means that not all
      hardware properties for the hosts are part of the template, but at least nothing is
      configured wrongly.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, a red bulb indicates, that the <classname>Host Template</classname> includes a
      hardware property, that matches none of the hosts and would be a bad fit. Nonetheless
      such a template might still be the right choice, since it can be modified for an optimal
      fit in the follow-up page. Alternatively, the correct hardware properties can be set on a
      per host basis by the wizard at a later stage .
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/template-clone.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Cloning a Host Template
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Cloning a Host Template
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/template-new.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Generating a new Host Template
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Generating a new Host Template
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      If none of the existing <classname>Host Templates</classname> are suitable, a new one can
      be created in one of two ways: Either an existing template can be cloned or a completely
      new one can be created.  In both cases, a name for the new template must be given.
    </para>
    <para>
      For clusters with identical node hardware, it can also make sense to directly change the
      <literal>Global Template</literal>. Click <guibutton>Modify Global Template</guibutton>
      to go that way.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	Changing the <literal>Global Template</literal> affects all hosts, so when this has
	been done, after exiting the Hardware Wizard, make sure the head-node and login nodes
	are still correctly configured (they usually have different hardware or configuration
	requirements compared to the rest). If they aren't, add the correct overrides to their
	<literal>Host Template</literal> or assign the correct properties and configs directly
	to them.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-hw-prop-set">
    <title>Selecting a Hardware Property Set</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Using an existing HW Property Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Using an existing HW Property Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-menu.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Choose an alternative HW Property Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Choose an alternative HW Property Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      This page selects the <classname>HW Property Set</classname> to be used in the selected
      <classname>Host Template</classname>. It is the main source for the node's hardware
      configuration. Like in the previous page an existing <classname>HW Property
      Set</classname> can be used/cloned or a new one may be created. Most likely an existing
      set will be suggested by the wizard. Alternatives are selectable from the drop-down menu.
      The available choices are again color-coded indicating how well they match the detected
      host properties.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-modify_template.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Confirm HW Property Set modification
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Confirm HW Property Set modification
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Changing the <classname>HW Property Set</classname> at this stage, will affect the
      selected <classname>Host Template</classname>. If an existing <classname>Host
      Template</classname> was chosen in the previous page, changing it might affect hosts
      other than the ones being configured in the wizard. In such a case, the wizard will ask
      for confirmation that such a change is desired.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-select_hw_prop.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Select alternative values for HW properties
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Select alternative values for HW properties
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-existing-copied.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          HW Property Set in edit-mode
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          HW Property Set in edit-mode
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      A selected existing <classname>HW Property Set</classname> may be modified for a better
      fit by using the auto-detected <classname>HW Properties</classname> displayed at the
      bottom right. If multiple groups of hosts are being configured at the same time, the
      properties, where hosts differ, will have a drop-down menu to select the most suitable
      value. Once the desired selection is made, the properties can be copied over the
      existing <classname>HW Property Set</classname> by clicking the
      <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> button. The wizard will ask for confirmation, in case
      this would impact hosts not currently being configured. Finally, it will set the
      <classname>HW Property Set</classname> displayed at the bottom left into edit-mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-clone.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Cloning a HW Property Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Cloning a HW Property Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Creating an empty new HW Property Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Creating an empty new HW Property Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      The described behavior is analogous when cloning or creating a new set. The difference
      between the two cases lies merely in the <classname>HW Properties</classname>
      that will be pre-selected: While cloning will start with the properties of the cloned set, creating a new one initially will have none.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new-add_property.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Adding a new HW Property
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Adding a new HW Property
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/hw_prop_set-new-remove_property.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Removing a HW Property
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Removing a HW Property
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      In all three cases, the <classname>HW Property Set</classname> can be further edited by
      selecting different values for properties, adding new ones or by removing some of them
      (both from the context-menu).  Once the desired <classname>HW Properties</classname> are
      selected, click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to continue.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	If <literal>Modify Global Template</literal> was chosen previously, choices will be
	limited to select the existing Hardware Property Set or the global one.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-resolve-conflict">
    <title>Resolving Hardware Conflicts</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/resolve_hardware_conflict.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Resolving conflicts by direct property assignment
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Resolving conflicts by direct property assignment
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      If more than one group of hosts is being configured at the same time or if the selected
      <classname>HW Property Set</classname> doesn't match all properties of the hosts to be
      configured, then the <classname>Resolve Hardware Conflict</classname> page will appear
      next. At the bottom of it, the conflicting or missing <classname>HW
      Properties</classname> are listed showing the detected value for each group of hosts. If
      only a single property is missing, the wizard will suggest to add this property
      individually per host.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/resolve_hardware_conflict-sets.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Resolving conflicts by direct property set assignment
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Resolving conflicts by direct property set assignment
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      On the other hand, if multiple properties are missing, adding a directly assigned
      <classname>HW Property Set</classname> per host might be preferable and will be the
      pre-selected choice. There is not really a wrong choice here. To some extent, the chosen
      option is a matter of taste.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	One can also choose <guibutton>configure manually later</guibutton> to tell the wizard
	to ignore the conflict. Be aware, that this will result in hosts that are only
	partially or wrongly configured and hence will need to be corrected later.
      </para>
    </note>
    <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-per-host-hw-prop-set">
      <title>Resolving by per-host Hardware Property Sets</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/hw_wizard/per_host_hw_prop_set.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Selecting or creating a HW Property Set 
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Selecting or creating a HW Property Set 
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	If per-host <classname>HW Property Sets</classname> was chosen in the previous page,
	the set to be used for each group must be picked here. The Wizard will try to find an
	existing <classname>HW Property Set</classname> that already contains the correct
	<classname>Hardware Properties</classname> for each group. If such a set is found, it
	will be pre-selected. Otherwise, the only option is to generate a new set, for which a
	name must be entered, before it's possible to continue.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-gen-prop-set">
    <title>Selecting a Generic Property Set / Config Set</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/gen_prop_set.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a Generic Property Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a Generic Property Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/config_set.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a Config Set
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a Config Set
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To complete the setup of the <classname>Host Template</classname>, a <classname>Generic
      Property Set</classname> and a <classname>Config Set</classname> must be selected. The
      two wizard pages handling this are very much alike, and similar to the one for
      selecting the <classname>HW Property Set</classname>. Again, there are three main
      options: Using/cloning an existing set, or creating a new empty one. Since there is no
      auto-detection for the values in these two types of sets, there is no color-coding of the
      choices in this case.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/gen_prop_set-add_property.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting Generic Properties
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting Generic Properties
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/config_set-add_property.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting values for Config Classes
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting values for Config Classes
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      An existing set can not be modified in the current <classname>QluMan</classname> version,
      but if <guibutton>clone existing set</guibutton> or <guibutton>new empty set</guibutton>
      is chosen, the properties and configs can be added to or removed from the new set. If the
      hosts have IPMI, the IPMI properties might need to be set in the <classname>Select
      Generic Property Set</classname> page. On the other hand, in the <classname>Select Config
      Set</classname> page, the Boot, Disk, and Slurm configs, are the most likely candidates
      for settings that need to be selected and fine-tuned.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	If <literal>Modify Global Template</literal> was chosen previously, choices will be
	limited to select the existing Generic Property/Config Set or the global one.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-HWwizard-summary">
    <title>Summary Page</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hw_wizard/summary.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The wizard's summary page
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The wizard's summary page
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      This is the concluding page of the wizard. It asks for the final confirmation of all the
      choices made, before the corresponding settings will actually be stored in the
      database. At the top of the page, the configurations derived from the <classname>Host
      Template</classname> (hence common to all hosts) are shown in tree-form. At the bottom,
      the additional <classname>Hardware Properties</classname> and/or <classname>Hardware
      Property Sets</classname>, that will be set for each group of hosts on a per-host basis,
      are listed. In case of conflicts, they potentially override the values of the
      <classname>Host Template</classname>. Host groups with no per-host overrides are not
      shown here.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	If an existing <classname>Host Template</classname>, an existing <classname>Hardware
	Property Set</classname> or the <classname>Global Template</classname> was modified
	during the wizard procedure, this is the last chance to drop out. By clicking
	<guibutton>Finish</guibutton>, all the modifications are made permanent, and the
	configuration settings will be assigned to the selected hosts. The latter should then
	be fully configured, and after writing the changes (see <xref
	linkend="sec-Writing-Config-Files"/>), will be ready to (re)boot.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
</chapter>
