<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-LogViewer">
  <title>Log Viewer</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-purpose">
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <para>
      QluMan comes with a <classname>Log Viewer</classname> that allows to inspect important
      events in the cluster. Messages are categorized depending on the type of event, when it
      occurred, which component(s) it involved and how important it was.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-indicator">
    <title>Messages indicator button</title>
    <para>
      At the right bottom of the main window the QluMan GUI displays a
      <guibutton>Messages</guibutton> indicator. The button shows the highest priority of
      uninspected messages, as well as their number. Clicking the button opens the
      <emphasis>Messages</emphasis> window. The <emphasis>Messages</emphasis> window can also
      be opened through the <guimenuitem>Manage Cluster -> Messages</guimenuitem> menu item.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-window">
    <title>Log Viewer window</title>
    <para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata
      fileref="images/messages/messages.png"
      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>
        The Log Viewer window
      </phrase></textobject>
      <caption><para>
        The Log Viewer window
      </para></caption>
    </mediaobject>
      Opening the Messages window shows a list of messages sorted by time, the oldest message
      displayed at the top. The messages can be sorted ascending and descending by clicking on
      any of the column headers. Only the short text of each message is shown to keep the
      window compact. Hovering over a row will show the long text for that row as a tool-tip.
      The long text can also be seen in a separate window by clicking the
      <guibutton>Details</guibutton> button. The extra window makes it easier to read
      multi-line messages and allows copy+paste.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter">
    <title>Message Filter</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The message filter editor
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The message filter editor
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Not every message is of interest to a user, especially messages that have already been
      seen. Therefore, each user can create his own filter for messages by clicking on the
      <guibutton>Edit Filter</guibutton> button. A filter consist of a number of matches shown
      as rows, with an action, as well as a default action. The filtering process goes through
      the rows one by one. If all fields set in a row match a message, then the action set for
      that row is executed: Either the message will be hidden or included in the messages
      window. If none of the rows match a message, the default action applies to it.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is one message filter per cluster connection tab. It can be freely edited. The
      message filter remains in effect till the tab for the cluster is closed. The filter can
      also be saved as a user-specific setting, so it is reloaded the next time a connection to
      the cluster is opened again. Alternatively, the filter can be reset to the last saved
      config or cleared so that the viewer starts without any filtering.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-default">
      <title>Default Action</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata
          fileref="images/messages/filter_default.png"
          width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>
            Setting the default action
          </phrase></textobject>
          <caption><para>
            Setting the default action
          </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	A filter can be constructed as a positive or negative filter. This means it can <emphasis
	role="bold">hide</emphasis> all messages that are not specifically matched or <emphasis
	role="bold">show</emphasis> all messages that are not specifically chosen as hidden. The
	default action can be chosen at the bottom left corner of the message filter window.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-add">
      <title>Adding a Filter</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/messages/filter_add.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
            Adding a filter
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
            Adding a filter
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/messages/filter_add2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
            A new filter row
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
            A new filter row
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	A new filter row can be added by selecting <guimenuitem>Add filter</guimenuitem> from
	the context menu. The new filter has an action of hide and ignores all fields. It
	therefore hides all messages. To be useful, at least one
	column should be changed through the context menu, to match only some messages. The
	context menu in each column contains the possible values the filter can match against
	in that column. The <emphasis>Origin</emphasis> and <emphasis>Short</emphasis>
	columns can also be edited freely by double clicking them. The action for the row can
	be changed between <emphasis>Hide</emphasis> and <emphasis>Show</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-seen">
      <title>Filtering Seen Messages</title>
     <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_seen.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Configuring the Seen flag
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Configuring the Seen flag
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
 	The most common filter is to hide messages with the <emphasis>Seen</emphasis> flag. It
 	is recommended, to always start a new filter by adding a row with action
 	<emphasis>Hide</emphasis> and the seen column set to <emphasis>Seen</emphasis>.  If
 	none of the filter rows match against the <emphasis>Seen</emphasis> flag, then it will
 	have no effect in the <classname>Messages window</classname>.  The
 	<emphasis>Seen</emphasis> filter can also be toggled between <emphasis>Seen</emphasis>
 	and <emphasis>Unseen</emphasis> by clicking the checkmark. The column can only be
 	disabled by selecting <emphasis>Ignore</emphasis> from the context menu.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-priority">
      <title>Filtering by Priority</title>
      <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_priority.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Setting the priority value
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Setting the priority value
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
	Messages can be purely informational, warnings or errors. Informational messages
	include information about nodes coming online or the server being restarted. There are
	usually a lot of informational messages and they can be safely ignored. On the other
	hand, warnings and errors should be inspected more carefully. In the Log Viewer, the
	priority of a message is <emphasis role="bold">color-coded</emphasis> for quicker
	visual recognition. Informational messages are green, warnings yellow and errors
	red. The highest priority of any shown message is also shown in the
	<guibutton>Messages</guibutton> button in the lower right corner of the main
	window. This indicates at a single glance, if anything important happened recently.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-origin">
      <title>Filtering by Origin</title>
      <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_origin.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Configuring the Origin filter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Configuring the Origin filter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
	The origin of a message shows the node or service that generated the message. When
	configuring the filter, the origin can also be expressed as a hostlist to match
	multiple hosts.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-category">
      <title>Filtering by Category</title>
      <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_category.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Configuring the Category filter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Configuring the Category filter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
	Messages fall into different categories, pooling similar messages for easier
	filtering. Generally information is categorized under <emphasis>Misc</emphasis>, while
	messages about nodes becoming online or going offline under category
	<emphasis>Online</emphasis>. The <emphasis>Licensing</emphasis> category includes all
	messages concerning changes in the license status. This could be something simple as a
	reminder that the license key expires soon. Or more important, a warning or error, that
	the cluster, as currently configured, exceeds the available license count. The last
	category is <emphasis>Exception</emphasis>. It usually signals a software error, that
	should be reported.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-short">
      <title>Filtering by Short text</title>
      <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_short.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Configuring the Short filter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Configuring the Short filter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
	Messages may also be filtered by their short description. Like
	<emphasis>Origin</emphasis>, this column can be edited by double clicking. Short
	descriptions are matched using standard regular expressions. To match only part of a
	short description, prefix and/or suffix the text by ".*" to match any remaining
	characters.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter-example">
      <title>A Filtering Example</title>
      <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/messages/filter_example.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          A complex example filter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          A complex example filter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
	The example filter shows a more involved setup: It contains five rows showing how rows
	can be combined to achieve the desired filtering result. The default action for this
	filter is set to <emphasis>show messages</emphasis>. Hence, only messages that are
	explicitly filtered as <emphasis>not wanted</emphasis> will be hidden.
      </para>
      <para>
	Row 1 excludes messages with the <emphasis>seen</emphasis> flag set. Rows number 2 and
	3 might look odd at first, because their action is the same as the default action:
	<emphasis>Show</emphasis>. But these two rows prevent any of the later rows from hiding
	messages with priority <emphasis>error</emphasis> or
	<emphasis>warning</emphasis>. In other words, warnings and errors will always be
	shown, no matter what additional filter rows follow. Row number 4 hides messages in the
	category <emphasis>online</emphasis> and row 5 hides messages that originate from hosts
	matching the hostlist "vm-[0-9]".
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
