<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-LogViewer">
  <title>Log Viewer</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-purpose">
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <para>
      Often things happen when one is not looking. For that reason Qluman keeps a log of
      messages showing what happened, when, where and how important the event was.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-indicator">
    <title>Messages indicator button</title>
    <para>
      At the right bottom of the main window qluman-qt displays a
      <guibutton>Messages</guibutton>. The button shows the highest priority of pending
      messages as well as the number of messages pending. Clicking the button opens the
      <emphasis>Messages</emphasis> window. The <emphasis>Messages</emphasis> window can
      also be opened through the Manage Cluster -> Messages menu item.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-window">
    <title>Log Viewer window</title>
    <para>
      Opening the Messages window shows a list of messages sorted by time with the oldest
      message at the top. The messages can be sorted ascending and descending by clicking on
      any of the column headers. Only the short text of each message is shown to keep the
      window compact. Hovering over a row will show the long text for that row as tool-tip.
      The long text can also be seen in a separate window by clicking the
      <guibutton>Details</guibutton> button. The extra window makes it easier to read
      multi-line messages and allows copy+paste.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-LogViewer-filter">
    <title>Message Filter</title>
    <para>
      Not every message is of interest to a user, especially messages that have already been
      seen. Each user can create their own filter for messages by clicking on the
      <guibutton>Edit Filter</guibutton>. Filter consist of a number of matches shown as rows
      with an action as well as a default action. The filtering process goes through
      the rows one by one and if all fields in a row that are set match a message then the
      action set for the row is executed, the message is hidden from view or included in the
      messages window. If none of the rows match a message the default action is taken.
    </para>
    <para>
      The most common filter is to hide message with the <emphasis>seen</emphasis> flag.
      Without this entry the seen flag has no effect. The filter can be freely edited
      and can be saved to act as the new default filter or reset to the filter that was saved
      last.
    </para>
    <!--cbox(file: messages/messages.png)-->
    <!--cbox(file: messages/messages_filter.png)-->
  </section>
</chapter>
