<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-Look-Feel">
  <title>Customizing the Look&amp;Feel</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Look-Feel-Overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      There are three aspects of <application>QluMan's</application> appearance that can be
      customized: Fonts, colors and widget style. Since QluMan is a QT application, it's
      Look&amp;Feel can be controlled with <link
      xlink:href="http://www.kde.org/___blank___">KDE</link> tools. Select the
      <guimenuitem>Manage Cluster->Preferences</guimenuitem> menu entry to bring up the KDE
      <classname>System Settings</classname> dialog. Now click on the <classname>Application
      Appearance</classname> icon and you'll have the options to modify fonts, colors and
      style.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Look-Feel-Fonts">
    <title>Customizing Fonts</title>
    <para>
      When you click on the <guiicon>Fonts</guiicon> icon, you'll see a list of different font
      identifiers, for which you can change the font settings. The relevant identifiers
      affecting <application>QluMan</application> are: <literal>General</literal>,
      <literal>Menu</literal> and <literal>Window Title</literal>. Changing one of the values
      and clicking the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button changes the corresponding font on
      the fly.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Look-Feel-Colors">
    <title>Customizing Colors</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/look-and-feel/system_settings_colors.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Customizing QluMan's colors
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Customizing QluMan's colors
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Click on the <guiicon>Colors</guiicon> icon and choose the
      <guimenuitem>Colors</guimenuitem> tab. There you can adjust the color of the different
      elements of the <application>QluMan GUI</application>. You can narrow down the color
      identifiers to the ones affecting particular GUI elements, by choosing a specific color
      set with the corresponding pull-down menu. Changing one of the values and clicking the
      <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button, changes the corresponding color on the fly.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Look-Feel-Clone">
    <title>Cloning KDE Settings</title>
    <para>
      If you're using <firstterm>KDE4</firstterm> on you're desktop, instead of configuring
      using the <classname>System Settings</classname> dialog, you can also move
      <filename>/root/.kde/share/config</filename> to
      <filename>/root/.kde/share/config.bak</filename> and copy your personal configured
      <filename>.kde/share/config</filename> directory to
      <filename>/root/.kde/share</filename>. As long as you're not using any non-standard KDE
      themes, this should just apply the favorite desktop settings you're familiar with to
      <application>QluMan</application>, when running it on a remote machine like the cluster
      head- or FE-node (restart of QluMan GUI required).
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Look-Feel-Widget">
    <title>Customizing the Widget Style</title>
    <para>
      Changing the widget style can be a little more involved. First you need to start the QT
      configurator <application>qtconfig</application> and choose a GUI style (default is
      QtCurve). The following assumes, you're running <application>qluman-qt</application> on
      the head- or FE-node. In case you have it installed on your workstation, just execute
      <application>qtconfig</application> there.
      <screen>
<prompt>0 user@workstation ~ $</prompt>
<command>ssh -X root@servername qtconfig</command>
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/look-and-feel/qtconfig.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a widget style
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a widget style
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      When you're done, select <guimenuitem>File->Save</guimenuitem>
      and you'll already see the changes. After this, you can exit
      <application>qtconfig</application>. If you want further customization of the widget
      style (note that only some styles are configurable, among them QtCurve), you can now go
      back to the <classname>Application Appearance</classname> dialog (see above), click on
      the <guiicon>Style</guiicon> icon, choose the style you've selected in
      <application>qtconfig</application> as <literal>Widget style</literal> and press the
      <guibutton>Configure...</guibutton> button. You'll then see a large number of options for
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/look-and-feel/system_settings_style.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Customizing the QtCurve widget style
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Customizing the QtCurve widget style
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      customization. When you're satisfied with your modifications, press the
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button and finally the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button of
      the <classname>Style - System Settings</classname> window. Note, that you will see the
      resulting changes only after performing some actions (pressing a button, etc.)  in the
      <application>QluMan GUI</application>.
    </para>
    <para>
      For additional widget style variants apart from the default of QtCurve, you can
      install additional kde-style packages (.e.g <package>kde-style-oxygen</package>) on the
      machine, where you're executing the <application>QluMan GUI</application>.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

