<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-Other-Configs">
  <title>Other Configs</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-Qlustar-OS-Images">
    <title>Qlustar OS Images</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/QlustarImages/main.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The Qlustar OS Image configuration window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The Qlustar OS Image configuration window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Qlustar OS images can be defined and configured in the <classname>Qlustar
      Images</classname> dialog accessible via <guimenuitem>Manage
      Configs</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>Qlustar Images</guimenuitem>. Each image has a unique
      name, a flavor (e.g. <classname>trusty</classname>), a version, an optional <link
      linkend="sec-UnionFS-Chroots">chroot</link> and one or more image modules.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sec-Image-Versioning">
      <title>Image Versioning</title>
      <para>
	Currently available image versions are 9, 9.1 (both meta-versions), 9.1.0 and
	9.1.1. Note, that selecting meta-versions (like e.g. 9) has implications on the update
	process. They allow tracking the newest x.y (x.y.z) releases automatically. Example: If
	you have installed version 9 of the modules, you will currently get the 9.1 (most
	recent 9.y) versions, but when 9.2 will be
	available, <code>apt-get dist-upgrade</code> will update to 9.2 versions
	automatically. So with this choice, updates will usually include larger changes,
	since new <emphasis role="bold">feature</emphasis> releases (like 9.2) will
	automatically be installed.
      </para>
      <para>
	Similarly, if you have selected the 9.1 version (currently default after a fresh
	installation) you will currently get 9.1.1 (most recent 9.1.z version) and
	<code>apt-get dist-upgrade</code> will update the modules/images to 9.1.2
	automatically once available. So this choice will update to new <emphasis
	role="bold">maintenance</emphasis> releases automatically. The most conservative
	choice would be to explicitly select a x.y.z version (currently 9.1.1), since then
	images will only receive bug fix updates without explicitly changing the version in
	<productname>Qlustar</productname>. See also the discussion in the general <link
	xlink:href="../Administration_Manual/index.html#chap-Updating-Qlustar___blank___">
	Qlustar Update Guide</link>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-Image-Properties">
      <title>Image Properties</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/QlustarImages/modules.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Adding a module to a Qlustar Image
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Adding a module to a Qlustar Image
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	A couple of images are pre-defined during the installation process. The dialog shows
	the images sorted by their names. Expanding an entry shows its configuration and allows
	to select a <link linkend="sec-UnionFS-Chroots">UnionFS chroot</link> via the drop-down
	menu. Each image contains at least the <classname>core module</classname>. Additional
	modules can be added or removed using the context menu when hovering over an
	entry. Only modules that are not already chosen are available for selection.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/QlustarImages/new.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Creating a new Qlustar Image
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Creating a new Qlustar Image
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	New images can be added through the context menu or by pressing the
	<guibutton>New</guibutton> button at the bottom of the dialog. Like before, you should
	then enter the name for the new config, choose a <link
	linkend="sec-UnionFS-Chroots">UnionFS chroot</link> and optionally provide a
	description for the new image. Existing images can be removed via the context menu.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-NIS-Hosts">
    <title>NIS hosts</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/nis/host_header.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The NIS host-header configuration window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The NIS host-header configuration window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <firstterm>NIS</firstterm> (Network Information System) is used to manage hostname
      resolution within a Qlustar cluster. For all hosts that are managed within
      <application>QluMan</application> itself, a corresponding NIS entry is created
      automatically. However, administrators might want to add other hosts that are not part of
      the cluster to the NIS database as well. To allow this, the creation of the NIS hosts
      database is split into a header part that can be freely edited by the admin, and an
      auto-created part with the hosts managed by <application>QluMan</application>.
    </para>
    <para>
      To edit the header part, choose <guimenuitem>Manage
      Configs</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>NIS Host Header</guimenuitem> from the main menu and
      press <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>. The top part of the window popping up can then freely
      be edited. When done press <guibutton>Save</guibutton>. Note that entries for the
      head-node are automatically created upon installation and should remain unchanged unless
      one of the head-node's IP changes. The final resulting NIS hosts file can then be
      previewed and written to disk by pressing the corresponding dialogs at the bottom of the
      dialog. Upon writing the file, the NIS database is automatically rebuilt on the NIS
      master server.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-SSH-Hosts">
    <title>SSH host files</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/ssh_hosts/known.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The SSH known hosts header configuration window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The SSH known hosts header configuration window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/ssh_hosts/equiv.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The SSH shosts.equiv header configuration window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The SSH shosts.equiv header configuration window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/ssh_hosts/authorized_keys.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The SSH root authorized_keys configuration window
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The SSH root authorized_keys configuration window
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To simplify ssh remote logins to cluster nodes, three ssh configuration files are
      provided and managed by <application>QluMan</application>: (a)
      <filename>ssh_known_hosts</filename> (holds ssh host keys of cluster nodes), (b)
      <filename>shosts.equiv</filename> (enables login without password between machines
      within the cluster) and (c) <filename>authorized_keys</filename> (used to
      allow password-less root login to nodes with the specified ssh public keys).
    </para>
    <para>
      The first two config files consist of a configurable header part, where additional hosts
      can freely be entered and an auto-generated part for the hosts managed by
      <application>QluMan</application>. The <filename>authorized_keys</filename> one just has
      the configurable part. Ssh host info for the head-node and a possibly configured
      frontend-node are automatically inserted during the installation process.
    </para>
    <para>
      Management of the three configs is similar to the <classname>NIS hosts</classname>
      dialog: To edit the header part of either config, select <guimenuitem>Manage
      Configs</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>SSH Configs</guimenuitem> from the main menu. Then
      choose the config to work on by using the drop-down menu at the bottom left and press
      <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>. The top part of the window popping up can then freely be
      edited. When done press <guibutton>Save</guibutton>. Finally, the resulting ssh host
      files can be previewed and written to disk by pressing the corresponding buttons at the
      bottom of the dialog.
      <note>
	<para>
	  There is no preview of the <filename>authorized_keys</filename> file, as this is
	  automatically written to <filename>/root/.ssh</filename> during the boot phase on
	  hosts, that are not head-nodes.
	</para>
      </note>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-UnionFS-Chroots">
    <title>UnionFS Chroots</title>
    <para>
      In most practical cases, a <productname>Qlustar</productname> image should be configured
      with an associated <classname>UnionFS chroot</classname>. Exceptions are single purpose
      images e.g. for Lustre servers. By design, images are stripped down to the functionality
      (programs) that is most often needed on a compute/storage node. This keeps them small
      while still providing fast, network-independent access to programs/files typically used.
    </para>
    <para>
      To complement the image and provide the full richness of the packages/programs available
      in the chosen Linux distribution, the UnionFS chroot (holding a full installation of
      e.g. Ubuntu) is exported via NFS by one of the head-nodes and technically <emphasis
      role="bold">merged below</emphasis> the content of the <classname>Qlustar OS
      image</classname>. In practice, this means that all files belonging to the chroot will be
      available on the nodes configured to use the chroot, but if a file/program is also in the
      node's image, that version will be used. Hence, this method combines the <emphasis
      role="bold">compactness and speed</emphasis> of the imaging approach with the <emphasis
      role="bold">completeness</emphasis> of a full OS installation to give you the best of all
      worlds.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/menu-manage_cluster/manage_chroots.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Starting chroot management
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Starting chroot management
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/main.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The Manage Chroot dialog
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The Manage Chroot dialog
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      As explained before (see <xref linkend="sec-Qlustar-OS-Images"/>), the chroot associated
      with an image is easily selectable via the Qlustar Images dialog. The management of
      the chroots themselves is possible via the <classname>Manage Chroots</classname> dialog.
      It is accessible via the main menu (<guimenuitem>Manage
      Cluster</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>Manage Chroots</guimenuitem>) and provides a number
      of actions related to chroots. Manipulation of the contents of chroots is explained <link
      xlink:href=
      "../First_Steps_Guide/index.html#sec-Adding-Software___blank___">elsewhere</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/select_chroot.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To <emphasis role="bold">specify a chroot</emphasis> to operate on, select it via the
      corresponding pull-down menu. This will show its description, as well as its properties
      like the NFS server that serves it, the filesystem path on the server, the flavor (edge
      platform, trusty/wheezy/...)  and the version of the <productname>Qlustar</productname>
      feature release (always being of the form x.y, e.g 9.1).
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/new1.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Creating a new UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Creating a new UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/new2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Creation process of a new UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Creation process of a new UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      When <emphasis role="bold">generating a new chroot</emphasis>, a name for the chroot
      must be specified and optionally a description of its purpose. Furthermore, you can
      select an NFS server where the chroot will be located (currently only one option), a
      flavor (aka edge platform) and <productname>Qlustar</productname> version. Finally you
      have the possibility to select <classname>Qlustar tasks</classname>. These are topic
      package bundles, each consisting of a collection of packages relevant to a certain
      field of HPC applications. Pressing the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button then starts
      the generation of the chroot. You can follow the rather lengthy process (count a couple
      of minutes) in its own window.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/clone1.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Cloning a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Cloning a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/clone2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Cloning process of a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Cloning process of a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/edit.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Changing the description of a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Changing the description of a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <emphasis role="bold">Cloning an existing chroot</emphasis> is mostly useful when you
      want to test an upgrade to a new release or for other tests. Pressing the
      <guibutton>Clone</guibutton> button, opens a sub-window in which you can specify the
      name of the new cloned chroot and optionally a description of its purpose. Pressing the
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button then starts the cloning process. You can again watch
      this in its own window. Editing a chroot allows to modify it's description.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/remove1.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Removing a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Removing a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/remove2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Removal process of a UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Removal process of a UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/manage_chroots/remove3.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Attempting to delete a used UnionFS chroot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Attempting to delete a used UnionFS chroot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <emphasis role="bold">Removal of a chroot</emphasis>, by pressing the
      <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button, first asks you for a final confirmation. If you
      then press the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button, the chroot will be removed
      provided it is not still in use by a Qlustar image. If it is, a list of
      images that are associated with the chroot is displayed. You would then first have to
      reconfigure these images to use another chroot before trying to remove again. <emphasis
      role="bold">Renaming of a chroot</emphasis> is not supported directly. To rename, you'd
      have to clone the original chroot, giving the clone the new desired name and afterwards
      remove the old chroot.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-Configuring-IB">
    <title>Infiniband Network</title>
    <para>
      For most practical purposes, <firstterm>Infiniband (IB)</firstterm> adapters need to be
      configured with an IP address (IPoIB) just like Ethernet adapters. If you have chosen to
      configure an IB network during installation, this section is mostly about how to review
      or change the initial settings. If not, IB has to be activated first in the <link
      linkend="sec-Configuring-the-Network">Network Configuration</link> dialog. An IB Network
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/network_config/infiniband.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          IB settings in the Network Configuration dialog
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          IB settings in the Network Configuration dialog
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      address IP and netmask can then be chosen there. The Infiniband network must not collide
      with the Cluster (Ethernet) or IPMI network. This is prevented automatically in the
      settings dialog. The Infiniband IP of each host is computed by mapping the host part of
      its Cluster Network IP to the IB Network. Example: IP Cluster Network 192.168.52.100 - IP
      IB network 192.168.53.100.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	This mechanism requires the IB netmask to be at least as large as the Cluster Network
	netmask. Hence, smaller values won't be selectable.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hardware_property_set/ib.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Setting the Hardware Property "IB-adapter"
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Setting the Hardware Property "IB-adapter"
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      In order to have a configured IB adapter during the boot process of a node, additional
      steps are necessary. It is not uncommon, that a cluster consists of hosts with IB and
      hosts without. Therefore, the pre-defined hardware property <parameter>IB
      Adapter</parameter> with a value of <parameter>true</parameter> must be assigned to a
      host, to explicitly enable IB for it. This is done most conveniently, by adding this
      property to the Hardware Property Set(s) used in the Host Template(s) for nodes with
      IB. If this assignment exists, Infiniband modules will be loaded and IP-over-IB will be
      configured during the boot process of the corresponding nodes with the IP mapping
      described above.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	The <link linkend="chap-HWwizard">Hardware Wizard</link> auto-detects the presence of
	IB adapters and allows to conveniently set the IB hardware property.
      </para>
    </note>
    <section xml:id="sec-Configuring-OpenSM">
      <title>Activating/configuring OpenSM</title>
      <para>
	In an IB fabric, at least one node (or switch) has to run a subnet manager to manage
	the IB routing tables. Qlustar provides <application>OpenSM</application> for this
	task. If the head-node is also part of the IB network, it's usually best to configure
	it to run OpenSM. This might have
	been chosen during installation, in which case there is nothing more to be done. If
	not, you have the option to run OpenSM on ordinary nodes too.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/network_config/opensm/port_all.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Activating OpenSM on nodes
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Activating OpenSM on nodes
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	In this case, it is advisable to run OpenSM on two or three nodes (not more) for
	redundancy reasons. It is therefore best, to configure this directly for the chosen
	hosts, rather than using a Host Template or generic property set. After selecting the
	host(s) where OpenSM should run in the Enclosure View, open the context menu and select
	<guimenuitem>Set Generic Property</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>OpenSM
	Ports</guimenuitem>-><guimenuitem>ALL</guimenuitem>. The next time the host(s) boots,
	the OpenSM daemon will be started on all its Infiniband ports.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/network_config/opensm/port_1.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Configuring OpenSM to run on a specific port
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Configuring OpenSM to run on a specific port
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/network_config/opensm/port_create_1.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Adding a new port for OpenSM
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Adding a new port for OpenSM
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	If a host has more than one IB port, OpenSM can also be configured to run only on a
	specific one rather than on all of them. The port can be specified by its number or by
	its unique ID. As this is an uncommon configuration and the unique ID is unknown
	beforehand, there is no preset value for this. To create a new value, first select an
	existing value, e.g. ALL, for the generic property <literal>OpenSM
	Ports</literal>. You can then edit the value in the <classname>Generic
	Properties</classname> box of a host. Editing the line and pressing
	<keycap>return</keycap> will create the new value. Beware that this will only affect
	one shown host. To assign the new value to other hosts, select them and then change
	the OpenSM Ports property through the context menu.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/network_config/opensm/option_add.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Adding an OpenSM option
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Adding an OpenSM option
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/network_config/opensm/option_edit.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Editing an OpenSM option
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Editing an OpenSM option
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	In some circumstances, it might be necessary to run OpenSM with extra options. This can
	also be configured via <link linkend="Generic-Properties">Generic
	Properties</link>. The only preset value is the empty string, so you need to create a
	new value for the options you require. First add the empty value of the generic
	property <classname>OpenSM Options</classname> to one host. Then edit the value to your
	requirements and press <keycap>return</keycap> to create it. Finally add/change the
	OpenSM Options generic property for all relevant hosts.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-IPMI-Settings">
    <title>IPMI settings</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/network_config/ipmi.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          IPMI settings in the Network Configuration dialog
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          IPMI settings in the Network Configuration dialog
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Configuring <firstterm>IPMI</firstterm> is similar to Infiniband and also involves
      multiple steps, because there are a number of options to set. If you have chosen to
      configure an IPMI network during installation, a larger part of this section is about how
      to review or change the initial settings. If not, IPMI first has to be activated in the
      <link linkend="sec-Configuring-the-Network">Network Configuration</link> dialog. There
      you can set the IPMI Network address IP and netmask. The IPMI address of a host is then
      determined with the same mapping as used when <link
      linkend="sec-Configuring-IB">configuring IB</link> and the same restrictions for the
      choice of netmask apply.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/hardware_property_set/ipmi.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Setting the Hardware Property "IPMI-adapter"
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Setting the Hardware Property "IPMI-adapter"
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Sometimes, not all nodes in a cluster have IPMI. Therefore per default, no host is
      configured to setup IPMI in <application>QluMan</application>, unless it is assigned the
      hardware property <literal>IPMI Adapter</literal> with a value of
      <parameter>true</parameter>. The easiest way to achieve this, is to add the <literal>IPMI
      Adapter</literal> property to the Hardware Property Set(s) used in the Host Template(s)
      for the nodes with IPMI. With this assignment, a node is ready for monitoring its
      temperature and fan speeds.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/generic_property_set/ipmi_initialize_add.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Allowing an IPMI adapter to be initialized during boot
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Allowing an IPMI adapter to be initialized during boot
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Enabling IPMI nodes for remote control involves two more settings. The first one is the
      generic property <parameter>Initialize IPMI</parameter>. Per default the settings of the
      IPMI cards are not touched by <productname>Qlustar</productname>. However, if the
      <parameter>Initialize IPMI</parameter> generic property is assigned and set to
      <parameter>true</parameter>, the IPMI card network settings of the corresponding host
      will be set every time it boots. Changing the value of this property to
      <parameter>true</parameter> and after booting back to <parameter>false</parameter> allows
      a one-time setup of the cards network properties.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/generic_property_set/ipmi_channel_add.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Setting the network channel of an IPMI adapter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Setting the network channel of an IPMI adapter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/generic_property_set/ipmi_channel_edit.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Editing the network channel of an IPMI adapter
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Editing the network channel of an IPMI adapter
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      The second generic property is the <parameter>IPMI Channel</parameter> to use. Per
      default channel 1 is used and this is the only preset value for the property. If you
      need to use a different channel, first add the generic property <parameter>IPMI
      Channel</parameter> to the <classname>Generic Property Set</classname> (or to a host
      directly) and then edit the value.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

