<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "QluMan_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xml:id="chap-RX-Engine">
  <title>RXEngine / Remote Execution Engine</title>
  <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Overview">
    <title>RXEngine Overview</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/overview.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The Qlustar Remote Execution Engine
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The Qlustar Remote Execution Engine
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <application>QluMan</application> provides a powerful remote command execution engine,
      that allows to run shell commands on any number of hosts in <emphasis
      role="bold">parallel</emphasis> and analyze their output/status in <emphasis
      role="bold">real-time</emphasis>. Commands fall into two categories:
      <literal>Pre-defined</literal> and <literal>custom</literal> commands. The RXengine has
      the following capabilities:
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The command can be a single command or a series of commands in
	    <application>bash</application> shell syntax.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The hosts are specified in <literal>Hostlist format</literal> or through a <link
	    linkend="chap-Host-Filters">Host Filter</link>, so that even large groups can be
	    represented by a short string.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The commands run in parallel on all hosts.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The network connection used for remote execution is both <emphasis
	    role="bold">encrypted and authenticated</emphasis>. It employs the same
	    high-speed/high-security elliptic-curve cryptography that is used for the
	    connection between the <application>QluMan server</application> and the
	    <application>QluMan GUI</application>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The output is <emphasis role="bold">analyzed</emphasis> and updated in short
	    intervals during the execution phase.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Hosts with equal output are <emphasis role="bold">grouped</emphasis> together to
	    display a compact view of command's messages.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The output can further be <emphasis role="bold">filtered</emphasis> by the return
	    code of the command and by (de)selecting <literal>stdout</literal> and/or
	    <literal>stderr</literal>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Pre-Defined">
    <title>Executing a pre-defined command</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/execute_predefined.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Preparing the execution of a pre-defined command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Preparing the execution of a pre-defined command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/predefined1.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Executing a pre-defined command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Executing a pre-defined command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/predefined2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Output of a pre-defined command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Output of a pre-defined command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Pre-Defined commands can be created using the <classname>Command Editor</classname> (see
      <xref linkend="sec-RXE-Command-Editor"/> for details). To execute a pre-defined command,
      open the pull-down menu of the <guibutton>Execute button</guibutton> at the bottom of the
      <classname>Enclosure View</classname> and select an entry. This opens a new
      <classname>Command Execution</classname> window for pre-defined commands. At the very top
      of it, the selected pre-defined command is shown. It can be changed if required. Below
      that is a list of the arguments, the selected command accepts. <guilabel>Execute
      on</guilabel> is always present showing where the command will be executed. If defined,
      additional arguments of the command are displayed underneath. Further below, the final
      command is shown, with its arguments inserted at the right places. The command will be
      executed upon clicking the <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> button.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/execute_predefined2.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Preparing the execution of a pre-defined command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Preparing the execution of a pre-defined command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/predefined3.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting hosts for execution
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting hosts for execution
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/predefined4.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Using a host-filter for selecting hosts
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Using a host-filter for selecting hosts
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Arguments to a pre-defined command can be set fixed to a <link
      linkend="chap-Host-Filters">Host Filter</link> , in which case the filter and its
      resulting hostlist are shown as plain text and can not be edited. Optionally,
      specification of arguments in Hostlist format may also be left up to the user. In that
      case, a combo-box is shown, followed by the evaluation of the specified input shown as
      plain text. When hosts were selected in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname>, the
      combo-box will contain the hostlist corresponding to the selection as default. The text
      can be edited directly or a filter can be chosen from the dropdown menu. Any argument
      starting with "%" is assumed to be a filter. If this is not intended, the "%" must be
      escaped by another "%", but only at the start of an argument. For more details about
      specifying arguments in pre-defined commands see <xref
      linkend="sec-RXE-Command-Editor"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Custom">
    <title>Executing a custom command</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/enclosure_view/execute.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Preparing the execution of a custom command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Preparing the execution of a custom command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/main.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The RXengine window for custom commands
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The RXengine window for custom commands
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      To execute a custom command, open the pull-down menu of the <guimenu>Execute
      button</guimenu> at the bottom of the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> and select
      custom command from the menu. This opens a new blank <classname>Command
      Execution</classname> window.
      <note>
	<para>
	  The initial hostlist is empty in the screenshot examples, since no hosts where
	  selected in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname>.
	</para>
      </note>
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/selected.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Selecting hosts for remote execution
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Selecting hosts for remote execution
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/update.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Updating the selection of hosts for remote execution
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Updating the selection of hosts for remote execution
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/past_command.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          Choosing commands previously executed
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          Choosing commands previously executed
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      In case hosts were selected in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> before
      clicking the <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> button, a hostlist representing these hosts
      will be present in the <classname>Command Execution</classname> window. This allows
      <emphasis role="bold">easy selection of hosts</emphasis> to run a command on by <link
      linkend="sec-Host-Selections">selecting them</link> in the <classname>Enclosure
      View</classname>. The hostlist can also be updated at a later time from the currently
      selected hosts in the Enclosure View by clicking the <guibutton>Update</guibutton>
      button. This makes it simple, to run the same command on different sets of hosts. When
      a command is executed, it is added to the <literal>history</literal> and can be
      accessed again later through the pull-down menu. This allows rerunning recently used
      commands without having to retype them every time.
      <note>
	<para>
	  Note, that the history is stored in the users home directory, hence every user has
	  his own. The preferred way to manage frequently used commands is by pre-defining
	  them (explained in <xref linkend="sec-RXE-Command-Editor"/>).
	</para>
      </note>
    </para>
    <bridgehead>
      Passing input to a command
    </bridgehead>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/input.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          RXEngine - Passing input to a command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          RXEngine - Passing input to a command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Sometimes it is necessary to pass some input to a command. This can be done by clicking
      the <guibutton>Input</guibutton> button near the top. Another text box will then be
      added to the window and will allow to specify, what should be passed to
      <literal>stdin</literal> of the command on each host. <!--FIXME: rewrite when
      implemented In future version the Browse button will allow selecting a file to be used
      as stdin. -->
    </para>
    <bridgehead>
      Command Syntax
    </bridgehead>
    <para>
      Commands will be interpreted/executed by the <literal>BASH</literal> shell on every host
      matching the hostlist. The full bash syntax is supported. Redirection of output to files,
      as in the last example, and working with variables works as expected. Please refer to the
      bash documentation (e.g. <code>man bash</code>) for more details.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Output-Analysis">
    <title>Analysis of Command Status/Output</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/execute/command.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          RXEngine - Executing a custom command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          RXEngine - Executing a custom command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      Once the hostlist is added, a command can simply be run by entering it in the command
      box and hitting the <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> button. It will then start in
      parallel on all listed hosts and the command output will be collected. Periodically, in
      short but increasing intervals, the <emphasis role="bold">output will be
      sorted</emphasis> and displayed. Hence, for short running programs you will see it
      immediately. Due to the increasing display intervals, long running and noisy commands
      won't cause constant flickering of the output, allowing you to more easily follow it.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Command-Status">
      <title>Command Status</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/df.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Tracking the status of executed commands
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Tracking the status of executed commands
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	After the <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> button has been pressed, all hosts will start
	in the <literal>Pending state</literal>. Once a host confirms that it has started its
	command, it will change to the <literal>Running state</literal>. When the command
	concludes, the state becomes one of <literal>Failed</literal>,
	<literal>Errors</literal> or <literal>Success</literal>. If the command exited with a
	return code other than 0, the host will enter the <literal>Failed</literal> state. If
	the command exited with a return code of 0, but produced output on
	<literal>stderr</literal>, it will enter the <literal>Errors</literal>
	state. Otherwise, it enters the <literal>Success</literal> state.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/pending.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Hosts in pending state
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Hosts in pending state
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/killed.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Killing a command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Killing a command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	In the screenshot example, the hosts <systemitem class="systemname">sn-1</systemitem>
	and <systemitem class="systemname">sn-2</systemitem> were down, so they remained in the
	<literal>Pending</literal> state. By clicking the <guibutton>Pending</guibutton>
	button, a hostlist of the pending hosts is displayed. The <application>QluMan
	server</application> will start the command on those hosts, when they become online
	again. If you do not want that to happen, or if the command does not terminate on its
	own, then the <guibutton>Kill</guibutton> button allows you to stop the command. A
	killed command counts as failed, so <systemitem class="systemname">sn-1</systemitem>
	and <systemitem class="systemname">sn-2</systemitem> now enter that state. The command
	output also reflects, that the command was killed.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Host-Grouping">
      <title>Host Grouping by Status and Output</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/group.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Statistics about job status
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Statistics about job status
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Hosts executing a command are not only grouped by their execution state, the command
	output produced by the different hosts is also <emphasis role="bold">analyzed and
	compared</emphasis> to each other. Hosts with identical output are put into a
	group. Their output is only displayed once, prefixed with the hostlist representing the
	hosts in each group. For a quick overview, the number of hosts and groups is also
	displayed below each state button.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the screenshot example, two hosts (<systemitem class="systemname">sn-1</systemitem>
	and <systemitem class="systemname">sn-2</systemitem>) have failed, because they where
	offline and the command was killed before starting. The output of both was identical,
	so they form one group. Similar, one host (<systemitem
	class="systemname">ql-head-pr-t</systemitem>) completed the command successfully and
	builds its own group.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <guibutton>S</guibutton> buttons next to the numbers add or remove the hosts in
	each state to form a new hostlist. Press the button to include the corresponding hosts
	and press it once more to exclude them again. This is convenient, e.g. to quickly
	select only the hosts for which a command failed: Analyze the errors and later relaunch
	with an adjusted command. Another example: Select only the successful hosts to run a
	follow-up command etc.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Filter-OutErr">
      <title>Filtering by stdout and stderr</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/errors.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - A command with stdout and stderr output 
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - A command with stdout and stderr output 
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Commands usually output regular text to <literal>stdout</literal> and warnings as well
	as errors to <literal>stderr</literal>. In the latter case, the command ends up in the
	<literal>Errors</literal> state, because this is usually something that needs further
	inspection. The screenshot example prints two lines, one to <literal>stderr</literal>
	and one to <literal>stdout</literal>. Unfortunately Unix does not enforce any order
	between output to <literal>stdout</literal> and <literal>stderr</literal>. Therefore,
	as in this example, it can happen, that a small delay between the command output and
	reading from the file descriptors causes the order to slightly change.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/stdout.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Filtering stdout
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Filtering stdout
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/execute/stderr.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    RXEngine - Filtering stderr
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    RXEngine - Filtering stderr
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Some commands produce a lot of output. Error messages are then easily overseen in
	between the lines. Similarly a command might report a lot of harmless errors, that hide
	the interesting output going to <literal>stdout</literal>. To simplify an analysis of
	the command output for such cases, the two buttons <guibutton>stdout</guibutton> and
	<guibutton>stderr</guibutton> at the bottom of the window allow <emphasis
	role="bold">toggling the visibility</emphasis> of <literal>stdout</literal> and
	<literal>stderr</literal> output selectively on and off.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Command-Editor">
    <title>Command Editor</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/command_editor/main.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The Command Editor
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The Command Editor
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata
        fileref="images/command_editor/ls.png"
        width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>
          The definition of a command
        </phrase></textobject>
        <caption><para>
          The definition of a command
        </para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
      The <classname>command editor</classname> shows all the pre-defined commands in a tree
      view on the left. A number of useful commands are already defined by default. Selecting
      a command shows its definition on the right-hand side, where it can also be
      edited. Every command has a unique name/alias under which it appears in the tree view
      on the left, the execute menu in the <classname>Enclosure View</classname> and in the
      drop down menu of the pre-defined commands execution window. In the future, it will
      also be possible to limit commands to specific user roles, but for now all commands are
      unrestricted. A user either has rights to execute any pre-defined commands or
      none. Below the role selector, the command itself is defined.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Command-Editor-Sorting">
      <title>Sorting commands</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/context_menu_1.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Creating a new command or group
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Creating a new command or group
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/context_menu_2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Actions for menu folders
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Actions for menu folders
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/context_menu_3.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Actions for menu commands
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Actions for menu commands
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Commands are kept in a tree structure, grouping similar commands together. They can be
	sorted freely using the context menu to make frequently used commands easier to
	select. The <guimenuitem>Move Up</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Move Down</guimenuitem>
	menu items move a command or group up or down within the group respectively. The
	<guimenuitem>Move to group</guimenuitem> sub-menu allows moving a command up or down in
	the tree hierarchy. Groups can be created, renamed and deleted to achieve any desired
	hierarchy of commands.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-RXE-Command-Editor-Defining">
      <title>Defining or editing a command</title>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/new1.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Creating a new command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Creating a new command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/new2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Setting the name of a new command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Setting the name of a new command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/rename.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Renaming a command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Renaming a command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	To define a new command, select <guimenuitem>New Command</guimenuitem> from the context
	menu and set its name. The new command will be created in the group, where the
	context menu was opened or in the root, if the mouse is outside of any
	group. Initially, the command will have no definitions.
      </para>
      <para>
	To edit a command, it needs to be selected first. Then its definitions will be shown on
	the right-hand side. The name/alias of a command can be edited by clicking in the text
	box at the top and entering the new name. The check-box to the right of the name
	indicates, whether your name is valid. Press <keycap>return</keycap>, to save the new
	name and the check-box will become fully checked again. To undo editing, simply
	reselect the command in the tree view.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/execute_on.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Choosing the target hosts for commands
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Choosing the target hosts for commands
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/execute_on2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Displaying the result of a host filter
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Displaying the result of a host filter
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	A command can be executed on any host or set of hosts in the cluster. The
	<guilabel>Execute on</guilabel> field governs how that host or set of hosts is
	constructed. The default is <parameter>User input</parameter>. This means, the user
	will have to choose the hostlist, where the command will run, at the time, when it will
	be executed. Alternatively, the hostlist of the command can be preset by selecting one
	of the filters from the dropdown menu. If a filter is selected, the hostlist, it
	currently evaluates to, is displayed below it.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/edit.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Activating the "Edit" state for a command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Activating the "Edit" state for a command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/edit2.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Editing the actual command(s)
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Editing the actual command(s)
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Editing the command itself may take a while. To avoid conflicts from concurrent editing
	attempts by different <application>QluMan</application> users, only one person can edit
	a command at a time. To start the editing process, click the
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button at the bottom. After that, changes to the command
	can be entered. Commands will be interpreted/executed by the <literal>BASH</literal>
	shell on every host matching the hostlist. The full bash syntax is
	supported. Redirection of output to files and working with variables works as
	expected. Please refer to the bash documentation (e.g. <code>man bash</code>) for more
	details. There is one exception to this: A "%" character followed by a number specifies
	additional arguments for the command, as explained in more detail below.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/edit3.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Specifying input for a command
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Specifying input for a command
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/edit4.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Saving the command definitions
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Saving the command definitions
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	Sometimes it is necessary, to pass some input to a pre-defined command. This can be
	done by clicking the <guibutton>Input</guibutton> check-box. It will bring up an input
	text-box, where the desired input text can be entered.
      </para>
      <para>
	To finish editing the command, click the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button at the
	bottom. This actually saves the command text and input, if any, in the database and
	releases the lock on the command. This also scans the command text for argument
	placeholders and updates the entries in the <classname>Arguments</classname> box.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/edit5.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Using command arguments
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Using command arguments
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/arguments.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    Determining the type of command arguments
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    Determining the type of command arguments
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	The definition of command arguments use the same mechanism as detailed for the
	<literal>Execute on</literal> definition. They can either be left up to the user, to be
	filled in when the command is executed or be specified by a filter selectable from the
	drop-down menu. When executed, the <replaceable>num</replaceable> placeholders in the
	command text are replaced by the user specified arguments or the resulting hostlist of
	the filter. There are always as many arguments as there are placeholders in the
	command. To add an argument, edit the command text and add a placeholder there. To
	remove an argument, edit the command text and remove the placeholder.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject><imagedata
	  fileref="images/command_editor/testing_command.png"
	  width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	  <textobject><phrase>
	    The test command appearing in the RXEngine window
	  </phrase></textobject>
	  <caption><para>
	    The test command appearing in the RXEngine window
	  </para></caption>
	</mediaobject>
	In the screenshot example, the test command is defined to execute on all head-nodes
	(<systemitem class="systemname">qlu-dev</systemitem> is the only head node in the
	cluster). It has some input and two extra arguments. The first one is fixed to a
	<classname>Hostname filter</classname> that evaluates to any host starting with
	<systemitem class="systemname">beo</systemitem>. The second one is left for the user to
	be specified, hence, when executing the command, only the second argument is
	editable. In the screenshot, the <literal>ONLINE</literal> filter was chosen for this
	argument, but any other text would have been possible too. For easy verification, the
	command text, with all the arguments substituted, is shown together with the command
	input (if defined).
      </para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  In the example, the specified input is simply output by the <command>cat</command>
	  command, so in the output shown, it appears between the two <command>echo</command>
	  commands.
	</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

