<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "administration-manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xml:id="admin-man-sect-network">
  <title>Network Configuration and Services</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Network Services</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    This section describes the basic network configuration and services of a
    Qlustar cluster.
  </para>
  
  <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-ntwrk-config">
    <title>Basic Network Configuration</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary>
    <secondary>Basic Network Configuration</secondary></indexterm>
    
    <para>
      The IP configuration of the head-node is defined in the file
      <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> (type <command>man interfaces</command> for
      details), while <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> is the key-control file regarding
      the DNS configuration (see <xref linkend="admin-man-sect-dns"/>). Network interfaces can
      be brought up or down using the commands <command>ifup</command> and
      <command>ifdown</command> (see also the corresponding man pages). Typically, the
      head-node has at least two network interfaces, one for the external LAN and one for the
      internal cluster network. For all cluster-internal networks (boot/NFS, optional
      Infiniband and/or IPMI)<indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary>
      <secondary>cluster-internal networks</secondary></indexterm>, unofficial (not routed) IP
      addresses are used, usually in the range
      <parameter>192.168.x.0/255.255.255.0</parameter>, while for larger clusters the range
      <parameter>172.16.y.0/255.255.0.0</parameter> is often used. In the latter case,
      <parameter>y</parameter> might indicate the rack number.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        The cluster-internal network ranges can be conveniently chosen during installation.
      </para>
    </note>
    
  </section>
  <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-dns">
    <title>DNS</title>
     <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary><secondary>DNS</secondary></indexterm>
     
     <para>
       This section describes how to configure the Domain Name System (DNS).
     </para>

     <para>
       The file <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> contains the addresses of the DNS 
       servers to use and a list of domain names to search when looking up a short
       (not fully qualified) hostname.
       Example:
     </para>
     
     <screen>search your.domain
nameserver 10.0.0.252
nameserver 10.0.0.253
     </screen>
     <para>
       where 10.0.0.252 and 10.0.0.253 are the addresses of the DNS servers and your.domain is
       the DNS domain name.
     </para>
     <note>
       <para>
	 The file <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> is automatically generated. The DNS
	 configuration must be configured directly in
	 <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> by adding <parameter>dns-</parameter>
	 option lines to the relevant iface stanza. The following option names are supported:
	 <parameter>dns-nameservers</parameter>, <parameter>dns-search</parameter>, and
	 <parameter>dns-sortlist</parameter>. Get more details on these options by executing
	 <command>man resolvconf</command>. The <parameter>dns-nameservers</parameter> entry is
	 added and configured automatically during installation.
       </para>
     </note>
     <para>
       If the compute-nodes also need DNS access, they should use the head-node(s) as a
       forward-only DNS server. In that case the package <package>bind9</package> should be
       installed and the addresses of the DNS servers be entered in the file
       <filename>/etc/bind/named.conf.options</filename>. Example:
     </para>
     <screen>
options {
  ...
  forwarders {
    10.0.0.252;
    10.0.0.253;
  };
  ...
     </screen>

     <para>
       The compute-nodes must then use the cluster-internal address of the head-node
       (192.168.52.254 in the example below) as their DNS server. This and the DNS domain name
       have to be entered in the DHCP template file of QluMan as follows, so that the
       compute-nodes may receive the required information via DHCP:
     </para>
     
     <screen>...
option domain-name "your.domain";
option domain-name-servers 192.168.52.254;
...
     </screen>
   </section>
  
  <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-dhcp">
    <title>DHCP</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary><secondary>DHCP</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
      The IP configuration of the compute-nodes is done using the Dynamic Host Control Protocol
      (DHCP). The DHCP server is not only responsible to automatically supply the IP address
      and netmask to these nodes, but also additional configuration options like the gateway
      and DNS server addresses, DNS domain name and many other parameters. The DHCP server
      configuration file is <filename>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</filename> (type <command>man
      dhcpd.conf</command>) and is auto-generated by QluMan.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is a general or global section and a per node section in this file. The global
      section determines values that are to be applied to all the nodes registered within the
      <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename> file. On the contrary, the contents of a node section
      applies only to that specific machine and is created from the corresponding host info of
      the QluMan database. The following listing shows the default global section that is
      automatically generated by QluMan during the installation of a Qlustar cluster (cluster
      network address is 192.168.97.0/24 in this example):
    </para>

    <screen>option option-128 code 128 = text;
option option-129 code 129 = text;
option qlustar-cfgmnt code 132 = text;
option qluman-router  code 133 = ip-address;
option qlustar-cfgmnt
  "-t nfs -o rw,hard,intr 192.168.97.254:/srv/ql-common";
option nis-domain "qlustar";
option nis-servers 192.168.97.254;
option domain-name-servers 192.168.97.254;
option routers 192.168.97.254;
option ntp-servers 192.168.97.254;
option qluman-router 192.168.97.254;
default-lease-time -1;
max-lease-time -1;
filename "pxelinux.0";
log-facility local4;
subnet 192.168.97.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 {
  use-host-decl-names on;
}
    </screen>
     <note>
       <para>
	 If a cluster has additional internal networks (e.g. Infiniband), the IP address of a
	 node in that network is derived from its basic DHCP address and set automatically
	 during boot. The addresses of additional networks can be specified during installation
	 and in QluMan. Check the <link
	 xlink:href="../QluMan_Guide/index.html#sec-DHCP-Config___blank___">QluMan Guide</link>
	 for more details.
       </para>
     </note>
    
    <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-spcl-dhcp-opt">
      <title>Special DHCP options</title>
      <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary>
      <secondary>DHCP</secondary>
      <tertiary>Special DHCP options</tertiary></indexterm>

      <para>
	You can set the name of the auto-mount master map with the DHCP option 128 (the default
	name is auto.master). To modify it, include a line in the
	<filename>dhcpd.conf</filename> header as follows:
      </para>
      <screen>
option option-128 code 128 = text;
option option-128 "auto.specialmaster";
      </screen>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-ip-msq">
    <title>IP Masquerading (NAT)</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary>
    <secondary>IP Masquerading</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
      To allow direct TCP/IP connections for the compute-nodes to machines outside of the
      internal cluster network, IP masquerading (NAT) is configured by default on the
      head-node(s) during installation. This might be necessary e.g., when applications
      running on the compute-nodes need to contact a license server in the public LAN.
    </para>
    <para>
      All IP packets with unofficial sender IP addresses and a destination in the public LAN
      are then translated by the head-node to packets with its own official IP address. When a
      reply packet arrives, it is translated back to the unofficial IP address of the
      originating node inside of the cluster. The head-node works as a router in this case. The
      following example section in <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> (cluster
      network address is 192.168.97.0/24) shows, how masquerading is activated on boot and
      disabled on shutdown:
    </para>
    <screen>
iface br-ext inet static
  address 192.168.55.44
  netmask 255.255.255.0
  broadcast 192.168.55.255
  gateway 192.168.55.254
  dns-nameservers 192.168.55.52
  bridge_ports enp0s4
  bridge_stp off
  bridge_fd 0
  bridge_maxwait 0
  up iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -s 192.168.97.0/24 \
    -o br-ext -j MASQUERADE
  down iptables -t nat -D POSTROUTING -s 192.168.97.0/24 \
    -o br-ext -j MASQUERADE
    </screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="admin-man-sect-time-server">
    <title>Time Server</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Network Configuration</primary>
    <secondary>Time Server</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Synchronized system time throughout the cluster is crucial for its flawless operation. It
      is achieved using the Network Time Protocol (NTP) daemon. If the head-node has direct
      Internet access, publicly available time-servers on the Internet can be contacted and
      used as an accurate time reference. In order to set a list of time-servers, edit the file
      <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename> and add a line for every ntp-server (example ntp-1) to
      be contacted:
    </para>
    <screen>server ntp-1
    </screen>
  </section>
</section>
