<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="admin-man-chap-general">
<title>General</title>
<para>
Qlustar is a complete Linux distribution based on Debian/Ubuntu. The main focus of Qlustar
is to provide an Operating System (OS) that simplifies the setup, administration, monitoring
and general use of Linux clusters. Hence we call it a <emphasis>Cluster
OS.</emphasis><indexterm><primary>Operating System</primary><secondary>Cluster
OS</secondary></indexterm>
</para>
<para>
A Qlustar HPC cluster typically consists of one or more head-nodes, and a larger number of
compute/storage nodes. For better stability and security, it is highly advisable to separate
user  
logins onto dedicated FrontEnd (FE) nodes. The latter can run on real physical hardware or
(especially on small clusters with just a few users) in a virtual machine. Qlustar allows the
setup/configuration of a KVM FE node during installation. 
and also add storage nodes serving a parallel file system (e.g. Lustre). All of the machines
are usually connected through an Ethernet network. If fast inter-node communication is
required, an additional high-speed interconnect like Infiniband, Myrinet or SCI (Dolphin) can
be installed. Most of the time, the compute nodes are stripped down servers with IDE/SATA hard
discs, often without keyboard and mouse connection. Users typically access the cluster either
through the head or login nodes (if present).
</para>
<section id="admin-man-sect-networking">
<title>Networking</title>
<para>
The <command>twiddle</command> command is used to twiddle files. Twiddled files will be marked
with the .twid extension, so if I <command>twiddle</command> <replaceable>myfile</replaceable>
then it will  become <replaceable>myfile.twid</replaceable>. Errors are written to the file
<filename>twiddle.err</filename>.
</para>
<para>
An environment variable <envar>PATH</envar>.
Use <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>d</keycap></keycombo> to complete the input.
</para>
</section>
<section id="admin-man-sect-nfs">
<title>NFS</title>
<para>
This is a test paragraph in Section 2
<screen><prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>twiddle <replaceable>myfile</replaceable>
</command>
twiddling myfile.....done!</screen> 
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
listitem text
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
have a look at <xref linkend="Test_Section_1"/>. ok
also have a look at <xref linkend="sect-test-section-2"/>. ok
<command>
  
</command>
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
