<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Installation_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
  "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <xi:include href="Book_Info.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Preface.xml"/>

  <!-- Start of real content -->

  <chapter xml:id="Requirements">
    <title>Installation Requirements</title>
    <para>
      To install the Qlustar OS you need:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A DVD or a USB flash-drive (minimum size 2GB) loaded with the Qlustar installer
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A 64bit x86 server/PC (or virtual machine) with
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
	  	<para>
		    at least two network adapters
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	  	<para>
		  at least one disk with a minimum size of 160GB
		</para>
	      </listitem>   
	      <listitem>
	  	<para>
		  optionally a second (or more) disk(s) with a minimum size of 160GB
		</para>
	      </listitem> 
	      <listitem>
	  	<para>
		  CPU supporting virtualization (for virtual front-end and demo nodes)
		</para>
	      </listitem> 
	      <listitem>
	  	<para>
		  Internet connection
		</para>
	      </listitem> 
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>  
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	The only virtual machine (VM) we test the installation process on is
	<firstterm>KVM</firstterm>. Hence, this is the only VM officially supported by
	Qlustar. Furthermore, while nesting of VMs is supported, it will be rather slow to
	start a virtual front-end node or a virtual demo-cluster directly from within a
	head-node that is itself running as a VM.
      </para>
    </note>
    <note>
      <para>
	The Qlustar kernel is configured for cluster server hardware. Hence, it's possible,
	that drivers for some network or storage adapters on Laptops or other non-server PCs
	are missing. If you run into such problems, please post it in the <link
	xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/forums/installation/___blank___"> Installation
	forum</link>. Qlustar also has no support for secure boot (UEFI).  If your hardware
	uses UEFI by default, you need to configure your BIOS to allow so-called
	<firstterm>legacy boot</firstterm>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="Load-to-USB">
    <title>Loading the installer to a USB flash-drive</title>
    <para>
      Starting form Qlustar 9, we provide an ISO install image, that can be burned
      onto a DVD or be loaded onto a USB flash-drive. This section explains the USB
      method. If you already have an up-to-date Qlustar USB drive you can skip this
      step. But make sure that you have the latest installer to be found at
      <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/download/___blank___">www.qlustar.com</link>.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
	After downloading the installer image, verify its integrity, by executing
	the following command:
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      <screen>
<prompt>0 user@workstation ~ $ </prompt>
<command>sha256sum qlustar-installer.iso.gz</command>
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Now compare the such-generated checksum with the value that is published at the above
      download page. If the checksums are not identical, do not proceed with the installation,
      since that means the installer is corrupt (either due to hardware errors or a malicious
      attack). In this case, you should download the image once more. If the problem persists,
      also after downloading from a different computer, please post the incidence in the
      <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/forum/___blank___">support forum</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The instructions in this guide only apply to the latest version. With the downloaded
      disk image you can easily create a bootable drive under Linux as follows (note that
      the USB drive should have a minimum size of 2GB): Given that the downloaded installer
      image file is named <filename>qlustar-installer.iso.gz</filename> and that the
      device name of the drive is <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>, the following command 
      (executed as root) will load the image to the flash-drive:
      <screen>
<prompt>0 user@workstation ~ $ </prompt>
<command>gunzip -c qlustar-installer.iso.gz | dd of=/dev/sdb</command>
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Depending on the speed of your flash-drive, this can take up to 20 minutes.
      Attention: The above command will destroy all data on the USB drive or to be
      more precise, it will destroy the data of the device named <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>!
      So make sure to find out the correct device name of the drive. This can be
      achieved e.g. by executing the command
    <screen>
<prompt>0 user@workstation ~ $ </prompt>
<command>tail -f /var/log/kern.log</command>
    </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      at the shell prompt before you insert the drive. Just after you have
      inserted it, a message like 
      <screen>
<computeroutput>[sdb] Attached SCSI removable disk</computeroutput>
      </screen>
      should appear. In this case your USB drive would have the
      device name <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>.  If the above command finished successfully,
      you can use the drive to install the Qlustar OS on the target machine. This is
      described in the next paragraph.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter xml:id="Installation-process">
    <title>Installation process</title>
    <task xml:id="inst-process">
      <title>Installation process</title>
      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <title>Booting from the USB Drive</title>
	  <para>
	    Insert the drive in the server that you want to install the Qlustar OS on and boot.
	    Make sure to select the USB drive as the boot device, either by entering the BIOS
	    and changing the boot order or by entering a boot menu and then selecting the
	    drive. On some BIOSes the latter is achieved by pressing the key
	    <keycap>F7</keycap> or <keycap>F12</keycap>.
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Installation process</title>
	  <para>
	    If the server boots from your drive it will present a menu with the following
	    entries:
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/boot-screen.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Boot Screen
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Boot Screen
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    of which the first is highlighted. If you install via a serial console (e.g. IPMI
	    serial-over-LAN) select the correct entry <replaceable>(ttyS0/1/2)</replaceable>
	    depending on your hardware setup. Press enter to start the installation. After
	    the kernel was loaded you will see the kernel messages on the screen followed
	    by some messages of the installation system. Finally the installer will present
	    a welcome screen and you can start configuring the system by pressing enter.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/welcome.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Welcome Screen
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Welcome Screen
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Localization settings</title>
	  <para>
	    In the first screen you can select the timezone and keyboard mapping. After you
	    have made your choices, selected OK and pressed enter, the keyboard mapping will
	    be configured according your choice.  If you have selected a wrong mapping the
	    keyboard will not function properly. If this is still the case after changing
	    the mapping to the correct value, you will have to reboot the server and start
	    the installation from scratch.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/localization.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Localization Screen
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Localization Screen
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Disk Configuration</title>
	  <para>
	    In this screen you can select the disk(s) to install Qlustar on.  If there is
	    more then one disk in the system you can select multiple disks and create a
	    RAID array (different RAID levels can be chosen depending on the number of the
	    disks available). The chosen disk (or created RAID device) will then be used
	    as a LVM physical volume to create a LVM volume group (the name of which can
	    be specified). Four ext4 filesystems <filename>(root, var, tmp, apps)</filename>
	    will automatically be created on equally named LVM logical volumes within this 
	    volume group.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/disk-config.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Disk Config Screen
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Disk Config Screen
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Home Filesystem</title>
	  <para>
	    A separate file system is used for the home directories. If there are additional
	    unused disks in the system you are offered the choice to use them in the next
	    screen. If not, you can use the previously configured volume group for this
	    additional file system. If you choose <guimenuitem>"Other"</guimenuitem>
	    then no configuration for a home filesystem will be done. In this case, you
	    won't be able to add any cluster users without further manual steps.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/choose-home.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Home Filesystem Screen
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Home Filesystem Screen
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Home Filesystem on separate Disks</title>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/choose-home-2.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Network (1)
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Network (1)
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This screen only appears if you have selected <guimenuitem>"Select disks"
	    </guimenuitem> in the previous step.  You can choose the disks and possibly
	    the raid level to use for the home file system similar to the previous dialog.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/choose-home-3.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Network (1)
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Network (1)
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Network Settings (1)</title>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/network-1.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Network (1)
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Network (1)
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    In this screen, you configure the IP addresses for the cluster and public
	    network. The installer has some logic to check for valid network configuration
	    parameters as well as suggesting reasonable values. The chosen number of
	    compute nodes <replaceable>NK</replaceable> in the cluster determines the suggested
	    cluster network address and other parameters. It doesn't have to be accurate,
	    just an approximate number will do.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note that Qlustar requires cluster-internal IP networks to be in a
	    <emphasis role="bold">non-public</emphasis> range. If you're unhappy with the range
	    suggested,
	    you can change NK to another number (e.g. NK=1000 suggests 10.x.x.x,
	    NK=200 172.16.x.x and NK=16 192.168.x.x).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You can also set the hostname (associated with the public IP) for the
	    new head-node. The name of the cluster-internal interface is 
	    <systemitem class="systemname">beosrv-c</systemitem>. Note that two network
	    adapters are necessary for proper operation of your cluster.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/choose-network-adapter.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    It's important that you correctly identify external (public/access to the
	    Internet) and internal (cluster) network adapters. If you select DHCP as the
	    configuration method for the public interface, make sure to add its IP address
	    later to the NIS and ssh related header configurations in the graphical QluMan
	    management interface. If you don't have any special reason for changing the
	    suggested address/netmask of the internal adapter, we recommend to leave them
	    unchanged.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Postfix is running on the head-node as the central <emphasis role="bold">
	    mail transfer agent</emphasis>. You need to specify a mail relay host
	    (either by name if resolvable via DNS or by IP) in your LAN, where mail
	    of the cluster will be accepted and redistributed. Root mails generated
	    on the cluster, will be redirected to a list of e-mail addresses, that you
	    can enter next (multiple addresses should be separated by a comma).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/network-1-ready.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Network Settings (2)</title>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/network-2.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Here you have the possibility to configure optional <parameter>Infiniband
	  </parameter> (IB) and/or <parameter>IPMI</parameter> network parameters,
	    if you have the corresponding hardware in your cluster.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If there are nodes with IB in the cluster, you first need to set the option
	    whether the head-node itself also has IB hardware or not. If it doesn't,
	    you only need to choose the IB TCP/IP network address parameters (defaults
	    are again recommended). Otherwise, you have the additional choice to run
	    <command>OpenSM</command> (IB subnet manager) on the head-node. Note,
	    that at least one node (or switch) in an IB fabric has to run a subnet manager.
	    Given the value of the IB network address, the host part of the IB adapters
	    IP address will be set from the host part of the Ethernet address of the node
	    in the cluster network. Example: IP cluster network 192.168.52.100 -
	    IP IB network 192.168.53.100.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/network-choose-ib.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    As with IB, if some of the nodes of your cluster have an IPMI adapter, that
	    is connected to a switch, you can enter the network address parameters that
	    will be used to configure its IP address. Again, the host part of the IPMI
	    adapters IP will be derived from its cluster network IP (see above). Additional,
	    host specific IPMI configuration options can be set in 
	    <link xlink:href=
		  "http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qluman-guide/___blank___">QluMan</link>.
	    Please note, that the configuration of IPMI adapters is hardware dependent.
	    The method, we use, works on most systems, but we can't give any guarantee,
	    that it will work on yours. Please contact us in case of problems.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/network-2-ready.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Additional Settings</title>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/additional-settings.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    For the sake of system stability and performance, it is usually a good idea to
	    <emphasis role="bold">separate user from system activities</emphasis> as much
	    as possible. To achieve this, we suggest to run only system-related tasks
	    directly on the cluster's head-node(s) and have physical or virtual front-end
	    (FE) nodes for user access/activity. In this dialog you can choose to setup a
	    <emphasis role="bold">virtual FE node</emphasis> as a virtual machine running
	    on the head-node. If you decide not to do so, we advise to assign a physical
	    machine as a FE node at a later stage. The suggestions for the network
	    parameters of the FE VM are derived from the head-nodes values. Again, if you
	    select DHCP as the configuration method for the public interface, make sure to
	    add its IP address later to the NIS and ssh related header configurations in
	    the graphical QluMan management interface. The name of the FEs cluster-internal
	    interface would be <code>login-c</code>.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You also have the option to create a <emphasis role="bold">virtual demo-cluster
	    </emphasis> on the head-node, provided the latter has enough main memory.
	    When choosing the number of demo-nodes, keep in mind, that each one of them will
	    be configured with 1GB of main memory. Even if configured, the VMs will not be
	    started automatically though, so the head-node will be able to boot, even if an
	    insane number of demo VMs are chosen.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Please note, that if you choose neither the option for the virtual FE node,
	    nor the virtual demo-cluster, the necessary network pre-configurations
	    (bridge setup, etc.) for starting VMs will not be done. This means, that
	    you'll have to do a number of non-trivial manual steps after installation,
	    in case you find out, that you need support for VMs later on.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If you need a <emphasis role="bold">proxy</emphasis> to access the WWW, you
	    can enter the relevant proxy parameters here. To speed up the installation
	    of additional packages later on, you could copy the software packages on the
	    USB drive to the hard-drive of the installed machine. But note that the
	    advantage of this fades away over time, once more and more packages will have
	    newer versions/updates and hence will have to be downloaded from the Qlustar
	    repository on the Internet anyway. To use a 
	    <emphasis role="bold">serial device for console access</emphasis>, select the
	    next option and enter the device name. Additional kernel parameters for the
	    head-node can be specified next (typically, none are needed). Finally type
	    in the password for the root user twice.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/additional-settings-ready.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Edge Platform &amp; Package Bundle Selection</title>
	  <para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<bridgehead>Edge Platform Selection</bridgehead>
		<para>
		  Starting from version 8.1.1 Qlustar supports multiple so-called
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/qlustar/platform/___blank___">
		  Edge Platforms</link>. Currently the choices are 
		  <emphasis role="bold">Ubuntu/Precise</emphasis> and 
		  <emphasis role="bold">Debian/Wheezy</emphasis>. Please select your
		  favorite platforms. Multiple choices are possible. At least one must
		  be selected.
		</para>
		<para>
		  In essence, this option corresponds to the choice of what Linux
		  distribution you (or your users, if you're an administrator) like to
		  work with/develop for. Note that you can always add support for a
		  previously unselected edge platform later on by creating corresponding
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qluman-guide#UnionFS-Chroots___blank___">chroots</link> 
		  and
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qluman-guide#Qlustar-OS-Images___blank___">Qlustar images</link> using QluMan.
		</para>
		<para>
		  Technically, choosing a specific edge platform (e.g. Debian/Wheezy)
		  will cause Qlustar images based on Debian/Wheezy to be created along
		  with an associated chroot. The latter will hold a complete Debian/Wheezy
		  installation in which you can later
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/first-steps#Adding-Software/__blank___">add packages</link>. By assigning such an image to some nodes later on, you will
		  have a <emphasis role="bold">full-featured</emphasis> Debian Wheezy
		  installation available on these nodes, once they have booted over the
		  network. Since multiple edge platforms are available, it is fully
		  supported and easily achieved to have subsets of nodes running
		  Ubuntu/Precise and Debian/Wheezy
		  <emphasis role="bold">simultaneously</emphasis> in the same cluster.
		</para>
		<para>
		  <mediaobject>
		    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/package-selection.png"
		    width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
		    <textobject><phrase>
		      Choose network adapter
		    </phrase></textobject>
		    <caption><para>
		      Choose network adapter
		    </para></caption>
		  </mediaobject>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<bridgehead>Package Bundle Selection</bridgehead>
		<para>
		  The default installation will only install a minimal set of basic
		  packages on the head-node of your cluster. Here you can select additional
		  package bundles to install. Among others, you have the choice of two
		  workload managers: Slurm and Torque. If you don't have a strong preference,
		  we suggest to use Slurm. In particular, if you intend to follow all the
		  instructions in the
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/first-steps/___blank___">
		    First Steps Guide</link>, Slurm is a requirement and is also sufficient
		    for a basic evaluation setup.
		</para>
		<para>
		  Beware, that you should choose Lustre as an option here, only if the
		  head-node itself is supposed to run Lustre services (MGS/MDTs/OSTs).  If you
		  merely intend to try out Lustre, it is recommended to <link
		  xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qluman-guide#Qlustar-OS-Images/___blank___">configure
		  an image</link> with Lustre support in QluMan, and assign it to some nodes of
		  the
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/#add-settings/___blank___">
		    virtual demo-cluster</link>
		</para>
		<para>
		  Note, that apart from Nvidia Cuda software, the packages selected here will
		  only be installed on the head-node. Selecting and generating boot-image
		  modules as well as the process of general package installation for
		  compute/storage nodes booting from the network must be done elsewhere. This
		  is discussed in the
		  <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/first-steps/___blank___">
		    First Steps</link> and the
		    <link xlink:href="http://qlustar.com/book/docs/qluman-guide/___blank___">
		      QluMan Guide</link>
		</para>
		<para>
		  <mediaobject>
		    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/package-selection-ready.png"
		    width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
		    <textobject><phrase>
		      Choose network adapter
		    </phrase></textobject>
		    <caption><para>
		      Choose network adapter
		    </para></caption>
		  </mediaobject>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Reviewing Installation Settings</title>
	  <para>
	    Before the actual installation will begin, the final screen shows a summary
	    of the settings, that have been selected/will be used (you will have to move
	    back with the left arrow key in order to scroll down in the summary screen).
	    If there are any parameters, you want to change, just go back and make the
	    required modifications.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/summary.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <title>Actual Installation</title>
	  <para>
	    The actual installation process will take a few minutes to complete. Press
	    enter when requested at the end of the process. Remove the USB drive and
	    press enter again to reboot. Please note that the head-node has a text-only
	    console. An X server (graphical interface) is not installed, in order to keep
	    resource consumption low and eliminate package overhead.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/installation-finished.png"
	      width="85%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	      <textobject><phrase>
		Choose network adapter
	      </phrase></textobject>
	      <caption><para>
		Choose network adapter
	      </para></caption>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</step>
      </procedure>
    </task>
  </chapter>

  <!-- End of real content -->

  <xi:include href="Revision_History.xml"/>
  <index />
</book>
